<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The practice of godlines or brief rules directing Christians how to keep their hearts in a constant holy frame, and how to order their conversation aright. With an addition concerning self-examination, and the nature of faith. / By Henry Lukin minister of the gospel.</title>
            <author>Lukin, H. (Henry), 1628-1719.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1659</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 124 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 65 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A88645</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L3479</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E2107_2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R210051</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99868885</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99868885</idno>
            <idno type="VID">121241</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A88645)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 121241)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 241:E2107[2])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The practice of godlines or brief rules directing Christians how to keep their hearts in a constant holy frame, and how to order their conversation aright. With an addition concerning self-examination, and the nature of faith. / By Henry Lukin minister of the gospel.</title>
                  <author>Lukin, H. (Henry), 1628-1719.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <editionStmt>
                  <edition>The second edition revised and corrected.</edition>
               </editionStmt>
               <extent>[12], 166, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by A.M. for Tho. Underhill in Pauls Church-yard, near the little North door,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1659.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>With a final errata leaf.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Nou:".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Christian life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Christian ethics --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:121241:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE PRACTICE OF GODLINES; OR BRIEF RULES Directing Chriſtians how to keep their hearts in a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant holy frame, and how to or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der their Converſation aright.</p>
            <p>With an Addition concerning <hi>Self-Exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation,</hi> and the <hi>Nature</hi> of <hi>Faith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond Edition Reviſed and Corrected.</p>
            <p>By <hi>HENRY L<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>KIN</hi> Miniſter of the Goſpel.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Pro. 4.23.</hi>
               </bibl> Keep thine heart with all diligence.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Pſal. 50.23.</hi>
               </bibl> To him that ordereth his converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion aright, will I ſhew the ſalvation of God.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>A.M.</hi> for <hi>Tho. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hill</hi> in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard, near the little North Door. 1659.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:121241:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:121241:2"/>
            <head>To The Right Worſhipfull M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> 
               <hi>Elizabeth Maſham.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Eing now upon a review of this ſmall Treatiſe, to ſend it a ſecond time to the Preſs, I thought it a fit ſeaſon to dedicate it to you, both particularly to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend to you the practice of the Rules therein contained, and likewiſe that I might here take occaſion to give you ſome Directions for the right improvement of that affliction under which it hath pleaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Lord of late to exerciſe you. And although it may be ſaid, that this might have been done rather <hi>in the car, then thus on the houſe top;</hi> yet I have choſen rather to do it thus publikely, both for your ſake, that you might reckon your ſelf the more oblig'd to obſerve them, while the
<pb facs="tcp:121241:3"/>world is witneſſe that you wanted not ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice and admonition; and likewiſe for the ſake of others, that (if theſe Directions be of any uſe) others may have the benefit of them. I was much induced here to by the complaint which I heard you make, when God had brought you back from the gates of death, and <hi>Patience had had its perfect work,</hi> in bearing that heavy burden which you lay under, <hi>viz. that your great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt work was yet behind:</hi> reckoning it an harder matter to improve an affliction then to undergo it. And indeed ſo it is, as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares plainly by the inſtance of <hi>Hezekiah,</hi> who was a good man, and did much good in the beginning of his reign, as we may read 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 29. and he had the comfort of it when he came to lye on his ſick-bed, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 38.3. And how did he plead for the continuance of his life? <hi>Verſ.</hi> 19. Doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe upon a good intention, and hope of living (as he had before done) to the glory of God, and doing good in his ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration: But <hi>he turned aſide as a broken bow,</hi> Pſal. 78.58. He miſſed the mark which (without queſtion) he ſincerely aimed at. We read of his pomp and worldly greatneſſe (through the abuſe of which he entail'd a curſe upon his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple whom he leſt behind him) but little
<pb facs="tcp:121241:3"/>of his goodneſſe, only that he repented and humbled himſelf, and ſo ſaved his own ſoul, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 32.25. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Now theſe things are written for our inſtruction, that we might not fall by the ſame example of ingratitude. It is an ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of a Learned man (the Lord <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rulam</hi>) that prosperity belongs to the Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings of the old Teſtament, <hi>adverſity</hi> to the Bleſſings of the New. Something indeed there is in his obſervation, but I am ſure, correction accompanied with inſtruction, was then a Bleſſing, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 94.12. And with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out this it is not yet a Bleſſing, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.11.</p>
            <p>Now that we may know what uſe to make of affliction, or what leſſon we are to learn thereby, we muſt underſtand that God ſometimes ſends affliction on ſome ſpecial errand, with reſpect to ſome parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular ſinne. And this is evident, either when God dealeth with men by retaliati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, as in the caſe of <hi>Adonibezek,</hi> Judg. 1.7. or by puniſhing men in ſuch things as have been the inſtruments of their ſinne, as he made <hi>Jeroboams</hi> arm wither which he ſtretched forth againſt the Prophet, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 13.4. and many Inſtances there are of this kind. Sometimes God makes that which is the <hi>natural</hi> effect of mens ſinne, to be the <hi>moral</hi> effect, or puniſhment of it. Thus
<pb facs="tcp:121241:4"/>he puniſheth luxury with diſeaſes in the body, <hi>Job</hi> 20.11. Idleneſſe with poverty, <hi>Prov.</hi> 23.21, &amp;c. and fills men with the ſruit of their own doings. Sometimes God bringeth ſome ſpecial ſin to remembrance, and awakens conſcience to ſmite them for it, as in the caſe of <hi>Joſephs</hi> Brethren, <hi>Gen.</hi> 42.21. Sometimes God ſaith (in effect) to us, as Chriſt to <hi>Peter, What I do, thou knoweſt not now, but thou ſhalt know,</hi> Joh. 13.7. At preſent we may not know the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular meaning of an affliction, but may underſtand it better afterwards. But (as the <hi>Schoolmen</hi> obſerve) to ſpeak ſtrict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and properly, God hath no end with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out himſelf. But when we ſay, this or that is Gods end in ſuch a paſſage of his providence which he exerciſeth us with, or in ſuch a giſt which he beſtows on us, the meaning is, that it doth of it ſelf con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce to ſuch an end, or is to be improved by us thereunto. Wherefore till it be more evident, what is the ſpecial uſe of any af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction, we muſt conſider what improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in general may be made of it. And there are five things which I ſhall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound to your conſideration for this end.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Conſider what was your greateſt comfort, and ſtood you in greateſt ſtead
<pb facs="tcp:121241:4"/>in the time of diſtreſſe, that ſo you may know what to put the greateſt price and value upon, and how to prepare for what trials may befall you in time to come: for the remedies which you have found effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual at one time, will be uſefull to you at another; and we keep the receits of thoſe things by us which we have found to be good by experience. Was it any worldly enjoyment? Theſe I am ſure you com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained of as <hi>miſerable Comforters.</hi> Can you not rather ſay with <hi>David,</hi> Pſal. 94.9. <hi>In the multitude of my thoughts within me, thy comforts, O Lord, have refreſhed my ſoul!</hi> Oh let not <hi>the conſolations of God, be ſmall with you!</hi> Job 15.11. Labour for more clear evidence of his loving kindneſs; prize it more then life. And though you ſhould want many other comforts, bleſſe him for this as long as you live, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 63.3, 4. Was not the Word of God your chief ſtay and ſupport? Say with <hi>David</hi> Pſal. 119.93. <hi>I will never forget thy Precepts, for with them thou haſt quickned me.</hi> See verſ. 49, 50, 54, 97. Was not the teſtimony of your conſcience concerning your ſincerity, your great comfort and rejoycing? 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.12. <hi>Exerciſe your ſelf continually to have a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience void of offence in the ſight of God and man,</hi> Act. 24.16.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:121241:5"/>Secondly, Conſider what was your greateſt trouble in your affliction, that ſo you may take heed of providing ſorrow for your ſelf againſt the time to come. Was it a ſenſe of the neglect of your duty in any thing, or of any thing wherein you have exceeded? <hi>Job.</hi> 36.9. (For who is it that can ſay they have herein made their hearts clean? Say unto God (through his Grace) <hi>You will do ſo no more,</hi> Job. 34.32. Was it the leaving of any worldly comforts? Be looſing your affections from theſe things every day by the ſtudy of mortification, and take heed of letting your heart cleave to theſe things, for then you will have the greater trouble at part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. Was it the thought of leaving any that are dear to you, in doubt of their ſtate and condition? labour the more ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly (by your Prayers, Counſels, Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples) <hi>to have Jeſus Chriſt formed in them,</hi> Gal. 4.19. and learn to <hi>caſt all your care upon the Lord,</hi> 1 Pet. 5.7. that ſo you may with more comfort and ſatisfaction leave them hereafter.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Conſider what ſpecial expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riences you had of the goodneſſe of God in your affliction. Had you not received the ſentence of death in your ſelf, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.9. and yet God was 'intreated for you,
<pb facs="tcp:121241:5"/>reſolve with <hi>Divid, Pſalm.</hi> 116.1, 2. that you <hi>will love the Lord</hi> for it, and that Prayer ſhall be your conſtant reſuge ſo long as you live. Did you not find that really verified, <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. that when your ſtrength was gone, the Lord repented him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf concerning you, and was the ſtrength of your heart, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 26.37. Never diſtruſt his power or gracious care and providence whatſoever ſtraits you may be brought in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to. Did you not find his Grace ſufficient for you? 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.9. How oft have I heard you ſay formerly, That it is an eaſie matter to believe when our Faith is not put to it; or to caſt our ſelves upon Jeſus Chriſt for ſalvation in the time of health and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity? but the tryal of Faith would be when we come into ſtraits, or draw nigh to the <hi>King of terrours.</hi> Were you not in your own apprehenſion even ſtepping in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the grave? Yet then (through grace) you were able, with as much quietneſſe and confidence as ever, to venture your ſoul upon a Promiſe, and to ſtay your ſelf upon Jeſus Chriſt. This is one precious fruit of affliction. <hi>Tribulation worketh pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, and patience experience, and experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence hope,</hi> Rom. 5.3. The trial of Faith is much more precious then <hi>gold,</hi> 1 Pet. 1.7. In the Greek it is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, agreeing
<pb facs="tcp:121241:6"/>with <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, not with <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Or if (as <hi>Glaſſius</hi> thinks) the words are to be ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred <hi>pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ata fides,</hi> the former Subſtantive being put for an Adjective, yet the ſenſe is the ſame, <hi>viz</hi> that it is a <hi>tried</hi> Faith, that is more precious then gold.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, Conſider the ſmart and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vineſſe of afflicton, and learn hence what ſinne is, that brings forth ſuch bitter ſruits. Remember the weariſome nights and daies which you ſpent, and conſider how hell will be endured; if affliction on the body for a few daies be ſo grievous to be born; and learn to pity thoſe that are in the like condition. You know the heart of thoſe that are in affliction, <hi>Exo.</hi> 23.9.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, Conſider your own promiſes and reſolutions which you made in your affliction. When <hi>Sigiſmund</hi> the Emperor, asked the Biſhop of <hi>Colen, What he ſhould do to be happy;</hi> he bad him <hi>live as he promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to do the laſt time he had the gout or ſtone. Jacob</hi> promiſed what great things he would do, if God would be with him in his journey, <hi>Gen.</hi> 28.21, 22. but God muſt put <hi>Jacob</hi> in mind of his promiſe, when he had anſwered his prayer, <hi>Gen.</hi> 35.2. We ſhould learn of <hi>David</hi> to <hi>pay our vows to the Lord,</hi> which we make in the time of our <hi>diſtreſſe,</hi> Pſal. 66.13, 14.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:121241:6"/>Now for your help in this work, firſt write down theſe things which I have here propoſed to your conſideration. We have the writing of <hi>Hezekiah</hi> when he was ſick and recovered again, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 38.9. And ſo we find many other godly men in Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, leaving ſuch things on Record. What they ſaid in their affliction, what they ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered, how they praied, how God anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Be oft reading over theſe things to revive the remembrance of them, that you may keep your heart duly affected with them. <hi>David</hi> hath ſome Pſalmes to bring to remembrance, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 38. and <hi>Pſal.</hi> 70. that is to preſerve the remembrance of ſuch things as I have here ſet down.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Pray with <hi>David</hi> 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 29.18. that God would keep theſe things in the imagination of the thought of your heart alwaies, and incline your heart to him.</p>
            <p>And for the faſtening of theſe things, conſider,</p>
            <p n="1">1. It is a provoking ſin, and a ſign of an evil frame of heart, not to be bettered by affliction, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1.4, 5. <hi>Jer.</hi> 2.30.</p>
            <p n="2">2. We loſe our ſufferings, and are moſt miſerable (as <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſaith) if we be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the better for them, 'Its ſad indeed,
<pb facs="tcp:121241:7"/>to ſuffer ſo much in vain, and to have no advantage thereby, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.3. It would trouble us to take a great deal of unplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing phyſick, and pay dear for it, and get no good by it.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Where God intends good to any, if leſſer afflictions will not ſerve turn, he will lay on greater; as we may read at large, <hi>Lev.</hi> 26. and if he give over any, while they are incorrigible, it is in judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and ſevere diſpleaſure, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1.5. <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 4.17.</p>
            <p>Now my hearts deſire, and earneſt Prayer to God for you, is, That he would long continue you to be a bleſſing in the place wherein he hath ſet you, that your Family may be as it hath long been, a Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minary to the Church of God, that Religion may ſtill thrive under the ſhadow of it, and that the ſame Faith may dwell in your Children, which hath dwelt in their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, and Parents Parents; that they may ſtand up in their Generations, to fill up their places, and to be followers of them in their integrity and uſefullneſſe: For this would be the joy and crown of rejoycing of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Servant, for Chriſts ſake, <hi>H.I.</hi>
               </signed>
               <dateline>
                  <date>May 30. 1659.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="introduction">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:121241:7"/>
            <head>THE INTRODVCTION, Perſwading to the practice of the following DIRECTIONS, and anſwering ſuch Obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions as are ordinarily made againſt ſuch a Practice.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F thou art one that fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt God, and wouldeſt gladly walk ſo as to pleaſe him, if thou de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſireſt to exerciſe thy ſelf unto godlineſs, to follow after righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, godlineſs, faith, love, pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, meekneſs, to fight the good fight of faith, to lay hold on eternall life, to get well through an evill world, and to keep thy ſelf unſpotted
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:121241:8"/>of it; this little Book was intended for thine uſe: and I hope thou wilt, if thou ſhalt read it, find it fitted there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to. I confeſs upon a review of what I had done, in drawing up theſe Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections, I begun to fear that I might injure the Reader by my ſtudied bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity: I thought ſome might overlook many things which are of ſpeciall uſe in a Chriſtians practice, becauſe I have not inſiſted on them, but heaped them together in ſhort La<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oniſmes; and that others (which are more weak) might not ſo eaſily underſtand many things for want of a larger ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication, or inſtances for the illuſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of them. For I confeſs I was the more incurious in the compoſing hereof, becauſe I had therein a chief reſpect to thoſe that have attended my Miniſtery, (wherein I have at ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall times more fully explained the things contained therein) who will be able by theſe ſhort Memorials, (I hope) to call to mind what they have
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:121241:8"/>formerly heard, and <hi>after my depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, to have them in remembrance.</hi> But I was a little eaſed of my fears, when I conſidered that theſe things were of daily uſe to Chriſtians, and therefore they would be put upon a frequent peruſall of them, whereby they may more eaſily both remark and underſtand thoſe things, which in one curſory reading might eſcape their obſervation: yea I have enlarg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſomewhat where I thought moſt needfull (which hath occaſioned that diſproportion of parts which thou mayeſt obſerve in the Book; for it is plainneſs and uſefullneſs, not neat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs or ſymetry, which I have aimed at. And now Reader, what arguments ſhall I uſe to encourage or perſwade thee to follow theſe Directions, when thou haſt read them? If there be any regard to be had to the glory of God, to the good of others, to the peace and happineſs of thine own ſoul, think on theſe things.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:121241:9"/>Firſt, This is the way to glorifie God in your converſations, when you walk blameleſs, and harmleſs as his Children, without rebuke, ſhining as lights in the world, <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.15. <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.16. <hi>Joh.</hi> 15.8. and the Name of God is diſhonoured by the looſe, careleſs walking of Chriſtians, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.23, 24.</p>
            <p>Secondly, This will be a means to recover the loſt credit of Chriſtiani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, Chriſtians are not ſo ſingular as they ſhould be, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.47. they are too much <hi>faſhioned to this world, Rom.</hi> 12.2. hereby prophane ones are hardened againſt the wayes of God; others confirmed in their prejudice againſt the principles of our profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, [the imputation of Chriſts Righteouſneſs to our juſtification, the neceſſity of his grace to our ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctification, the certain perſeverance of believers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>] and all the argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments which we can uſe to vindicate them from the imputation of che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:121241:9"/>licentiouſneſs, will never con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince gainſayers, unleſs we enforce them by the reall proofs of an holy converſation. <hi>See then that you walk circumſpectly,</hi> Epheſ. 5.15. <hi>that you may by well-doing put to ſtlence the ignorance of fooliſh men,</hi> 1 Pet. 2.15. <hi>That you may cut off eccaſion from thoſe that deſire occaſion, that wherein they glory, they may be found even as you,</hi> 2 Cor. 11.12.</p>
            <p n="3">3. This will be a means to gain thoſe that are without, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.1. and to provoke to emulation, thoſe that are within, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.2.</p>
            <p n="4">4. This will be a good means to make your calling and election ſure, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.10. compared with <hi>ver.</hi> 5. In the 10th. verſe the Apoſtle doth re-inforce his exhortation (which he had laid down in the 5th. verſe, by a new argument; as if he had ſaid, the rather give diligence to add to faith virtue, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to the end you may make your calling and election ſure.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:121241:10"/>5. This will be the way to have comfort both in life and death, the teſtimony of a good conſcience will be a comfort to us in every condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.12. eſpecially when we come to lye down in the duſt of death, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.7. Some will object (it may be) that this is more then needs, and why ſhould we impoſe any unneceſſary burden, upon Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians? To this I muſt ſay, that it is an unſavoury objection, and not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming a godly man. To enquire only what is neceſſary, and what we muſt do, if we will get to Heaven, ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gues more ſelf-love, then love to God; more care of our own welfare, then of the glory of God, or how we may do thoſe things which may pleaſe him.</p>
            <p n="2">2. If all the rules which I have gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, be not neceſſary by vertue of any ſpeciall <hi>command,</hi> (as I am ſure moſt of them are,) yet they are ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary as <hi>means</hi> to order our conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:121241:10"/>aright. But if thine objection be intended chiefly againſt this par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular modell which I have drawn up, after ſo many Treatiſes on the ſame ſubject; I confeſs then I ſhall not have ſo much to ſay againſt it; I freely acknowledg that many worthy men have laboured herein, more fit in many reſpects for ſuch an under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking then my ſelf: and I muſt leave every one to their liberty, to uſe ſuch helps as ſeem beſt to them; only this I ſhall ſay, that I think I have not <hi>only done that which was done before.</hi> Some have indeed writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten excellently at large of theſe things, but ſome Chriſtians cannot ſo eaſily read larger Treatiſes, nor ſo eaſily gather up the ſum of them to carry in their minds; theſe ſhort rules may be uſefull to ſuch; and thoſe that have leiſure and opportunity, may make uſe of them for the clearer explication of theſe. Some have written excellent brief Manuals, but
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:121241:11"/>have inſiſted much upon ſuch things as I have here purpoſely omitted, that I might not <hi>actum agere,</hi> as vows, meditations, and the uſe thereof in quickening affections, and ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ening reſolu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ions: if <hi>thou ſavoureſt the things that be of God,</hi> I dare com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend to thee what hath been written on this ſubject, by my worthy Friend M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Tho White.</hi> Others have written indeed excellent things on this Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject; but there is in their Books ſuch a mixture of Popiſh principles and ſuperſtition, that weaker Chriſtians which have not their <hi>ſenſes exerciſed to diſcern good and evil,</hi> can ſcarce without danger make uſe of them. In what I have here written I know nothing that is called in queſtion, (eſpecially in the Directions,) by any ſober man: for I have kept within the ſafe bounds of acknowledged truths, to free the Reader from all ſuſpition, (at leaſt from all danger) of being miſled into any unſafe paths. If any
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:121241:11"/>ſhall object againſt the ſtrictneſs of this exerciſe, or courſe of life, I need ſay no more to ſhame ſuch an obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, but to ſet before you ſome brief inſtances of the heathen piety, ſhewing how far they went by the light of nature in the obſervation of theſe rules which I have laid down; their high eſteem of godlineſs in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall, above all other things, they very oft diſcover in their writings; but we have frequent inſtances of their practice thereof, in particular duties, as Prayer. It is ſaid of <hi>Socra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes,</hi> that his life was nothing but a continuall Prayer, ſo frequent was he therein; one paſſage whereof is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported to be, <hi>Date ut ſim pulcher in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus, &amp; honeſtus,</hi> which is in effect the ſame with that of <hi>David,</hi> Pſal. 51.10. <hi>Create in me a clean heart, and renew in me a right spirit. Seneca</hi> is an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent example of Ethnick devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, (I know how he is accuſed by ſome, of contradicting his principles
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:121241:12"/>by his practices; yet it appears what their convictions were, however their corrupt affections might prevail againſt them,) how we ſhould im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove the conſideration of Gods om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nipreſence; See <hi>Senec. Epiſt.</hi> 10. how we ſhould improve the conſideration of his providence, <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 107. how we ſhould exerciſe virtue in every con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 85. how we ſhould ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply our ſelves to God in Prayer, <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 41. how we ſhould behave our ſelves in Prayer, <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 10. what reſpect we ſhould have to death and the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to come, <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 4, 12, 26. how carefull we ſhould be in the ſpending of our time, <hi>lib. de brevitate vitae,</hi> in which book he enveighs much a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt mens profuſe expence of their time, of which alone we may be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocently covetous. Of the choice of our company, <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 7. and our carriage therein. <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 10. <hi>Sic vive cum hominibus tanquam Deus videat; ſic loquere cum Deo tanquam bomines
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:121241:12"/>audiant;</hi> we ſhould ſo converſe with men as if God looked on, ſo ſpeak to God in Prayer, as if men heard us. And of taking an account of our ſelves every night, how we have ſpent the day paſt, we have an admirable example, <hi>lib.</hi> 3. <hi>de Ira, cap.</hi> 36. and this laſt was an ordinary practice with devouter heathens; concerning which, there are famous precepts of <hi>Pythagoras</hi> in his Golden verſes, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <list>
               <item>i.e. <hi>Nec prius in dulcem declines, lumina ſomnum,</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Omnia quam longi reputaveris acta dici,</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Quo praetergreſſus, quid factum in tempore, quid non,</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Si dicta &amp; facta per omnia ingre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diens,</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Ortu<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> &amp; veſpere cuncta revol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens,</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Offenſus pravis, da palmam &amp; pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mia rectis.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>The ſumme of which is, that we
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:121241:13"/>ſhould give no ſleep to our eyes, nor ſlumber to our eye-lids, till we have examined and paſſed ſentence upon all the actions of the day, approving the good, and condemning the evil.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vid.</hi> Arriani Epictet. <hi>lib.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 10. Auſon. <hi>Edyll.</hi> 8. Much more to like purpoſe we might be furniſhed with, out of <hi>Plutarch, Epictetus, De la Moth le Vayer, de la Vertu des Pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens,</hi> &amp;c. To ſpeak nothing of their putting out their eyes, caſting away their riches, retyring from the ſocie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of men, that they might devote themſelyes to a contemplative life; practices which our Chriſtian profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion doth not require, nor the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures allow. The former things ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the approbation of the Word of God, and the concurrent practice, of holy men mentioned therein, may ſhame Chriſtians that have more obligations upon them, more light, more means of grace, more aſſiſtance of the Spirit, then theſe heathens had.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:121241:13"/>Laſtly, Some may object againſt this courſe, that it is very difficult to obſerve ſo many rules, and this would make the Chriſtian life very burdenſome: To this I anſwer, Firſt with <hi>Tertullian,</hi> Apol. cap. 40. <hi>Semper humana gens male de Deo meruit;</hi> God hath alwaies been but little beholding to men, who grudge at every thing that God hath <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rom them: of old they would put off God with any thing, <hi>Mal.</hi> 1.8, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but they thought nothing too much for their Idols, <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.36. no not their children, <hi>Jer.</hi> 3.23. It was ordinary for the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens to object againſt the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Religion, that it taught many things contrary to reaſon, when in the mean while their own heathen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh ſuperſtition contained many things more abhorring from ſound reaſon, then any thing which they could pretend in Chriſtianity, as the Fathers in the Primitive Church
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:121241:14"/>commonly replied in their Apolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gies for the Chriſtians. <hi>Vide</hi> Tertul. <hi>de carne Chriſti, cap.</hi> 4. Auſtin <hi>de Civitate Dei, lib.</hi> 1. <hi>c. p.</hi> 14. Joſeph. <hi>cont.</hi> Apion. <hi>Origens</hi> conference with <hi>Alexander Severus,</hi> &amp;c. Such unequall dealing hath God alwaies had from men. It were enough to affright men from the profeſſion of Religion, if they ſhould thereby indanger their lives, yet they ſet light by them for maintaining ſome point of Honour, and can freely ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice them (in a duell) to revenge or vainglory: many would account it a grievous bondage to walk cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſpectly, to order all their thoughts, words and actions accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to rule, to whom a ſtudied carriage, and an induſtrious acting of the fooliſh faſhions of the times is no trouble: It would ſeem to many a burden too grievous to be born, to be tied to ſpend that time in reading the Scriptures (that they
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:121241:14"/>might learn ſuch ſavoury ſpeeches as would miniſter grace to others, <hi>Eph</hi> 4.29. and ſave their own ſouls to boot, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.15.) which they ſpend in reading Romances, to learn ſuch vain language as they muſt reckon for another day. How many are there, that would not for all that Heaven is worth, ſpend ſo much time every morning, in <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorning the hidden man of the heart,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.3, 4. as they do in adorning the outward man. I ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude this firſt anſwer with that of <hi>Picus Mirandula,</hi> Ep. 1. ad Nep. <hi>Non poteſt non extremae eſſe demen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiae, ibi nolle potius laborare, ubi a labore itur ad mercedem, quam ubi a labore itur ad ſupplicium.</hi> It muſt needs be the greateſt folly and mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in the world, to take more pains, and run greater hazards in the ways of ſinne to go to hell, then they need to do in the wayes of God to go to Heaven. Secondly, As
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:121241:15"/>Biſhop <hi>Hall</hi> ſaith, There is nothing to be gotten by idleneſs, but miſery here, and Hell hereafter: <hi>The king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Heaven ſuffers violence, and the violent take it by force,</hi> Mat. 11.12. A Chriſtians life is a race, a war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare; and he muſt run, ſtrive, fight, if he will win the prize, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.24, 25, 26. he muſt watch and pray, and arm, and ſtand faſt, and quit himſelf like a man, if he will obtain the Crown, <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.41. 1 Cor. 16.13. Epheſ. 6.13. Thirdly, Thou knoweſt not how difficult this courſe is till thou haſt been exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed therein: <hi>Non putant fieri quic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid facere non poſſunt: ex infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate ſua de virtute ferunt ſenten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam.</hi> Sen. <hi>Ep</hi> 71. who ever learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed any art or myſtery, but it ſeemed very difficult at firſt? which practice afterward makes eaſie: there is a myſtery in practicall Godlineſs, as well as in ſpeculative Divinity, which makes it ſeem hard at firſt; I
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:121241:15"/>know this is not acquired wholly by induſtry, and exerciſe, as other habits are, but exerciſe doth much facilitate it: Again cuſtom is the greateſt Tyrant in the world, <hi>Jer.</hi> 13.23. whoſe yoak it is an hard matter to caſt off, in thoſe things which afterwards we can eaſily contemn; how vain would thoſe wayes of ſinne ſeem to many which now they are wedded to? how eaſie would thoſe wayes of holineſs ſeem to them, the difficulty whereof doth ſo much affright them; if they would <hi>awake to righteouſneſs, and ſtir up themſelves to take hold on the Lord,</hi> 1 Cor. 15.34. Iſa 64.7. not wavering betwixt God and the world, <hi>Jam.</hi> 1.6. (for then they are like to be driven and toſſed, with every wind of temptation) <hi>but cleaving to the Lord with purpoſe of heart,</hi> Acts 11.23. <hi>Quam ſuave mihi ſubito factum eſt carere ſuavitatibus nugarum? quas am<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ttere metus fuit,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:121241:16"/>jam dimittere gaudium fuit,</hi> ſaith <hi>Auſtin,</hi> Confeſſion, <hi>lib.</hi> 9 <hi>cap</hi> 1. he had a long time been dallying with ſinne, and his thoughts were fluctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ating to and fro; but when they came to the conſiſtency of a firm reſolution, it was preſently a plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to him, to want his former de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightfull vanities; and thoſe things which before he was afraid to loſe, he could now joyfully let go.</p>
            <p>Finally, This practice will not be ſo difficult, as you may at firſt ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect: becauſe theſe rules which I have laid down, are a great help to each other. One that had never ſeen a Watch, or ſuch like work of Art, would wonder how ſo many wheels ſhould keep ſuch a conſtant orderly motion: whereas one that underſtands the manner of their motion, knows that one wheel doth protrude or thruſt forward ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and that the motion could not eaſily be ſo regular, if there were
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:121241:16"/>fewer wheels in it: ſo it is in this caſe, one duty puts forward ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and doth diſpoſe us to the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of another: or as in the body, labour or exerciſe begets an appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tite, when we have an appetite our food is mort pleaſant to us, and it likewiſe helps digeſtion, and ſo our food doth us more good and ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens us to labour; ſo the more we exerciſe our ſelves unto Godlineſs, the more experience we ſhall have of our own inſufficiency, and of the need that we ſtand in of a daily ſupply of the Spirit of Jeſus Chriſt; and ſo we ſhall more prize and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to improve thoſe Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances which are the miniſtration of the Spirit, as Prayer and the Word of God: And therefore if men ſlight Ordinances, 'tis an ill ſign that they have grown negligent in the practace of godlineſs; for he that ſets himſelf to walk ſo as he may pleaſe God, will find all means
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:121241:17"/>little enough to maintain the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gour of his grace; and the more we improve our communion with God in Ordinances, the better ſhall we be enabled to hold on in a courſe of godlineſs; ſo that as it is in the body naturall and miſticall, one member is uſefull to another, it is likewiſe in theſe duties. I may alſo add, that the benefits of ſuch a practice, (which I have before recounted) will abundantly recompence any di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>igence which we can uſe therein: which hath been confirmed by the experience of thoſe which have been exerciſed therein: as you may ſee in M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Rogers</hi> Seaven Treatiſes, where he tells us <hi>Treat</hi> 4 <hi>cap.</hi> 11. of divers godly men, who when they were at firſt put upon ſuch a courſe as is here preſcribed, looked upon it as a thing impoſſible to be obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved; but being perſwaded to make triall of it, they freely acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that they found and obtained
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:121241:17"/>more uſe of their knowledg, more conſtancy in their courſe, and ſweet delight in ſerving of God, then ever they looked for, and hereby they came to be better able to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form duties, to bear croſſes and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions, to ſubdue their affections, and to overcome their doubts and fears. Methinks the hope of like ſucceſs, ſhould encourage any that make Religion their buſineſs, to make triall of this practice; thoſe that have more objections yet to make againſt it, may find them an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered in <hi>Drexelius</hi> his <hi>Triſmegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus,</hi> lib. 1. cap. 7. And now Reader I may conclude with <hi>Tertullian de patientia prin:</hi> or in the words of Biſhop <hi>Sales,</hi> in the <hi>Preface</hi> to his <hi>Introduction;</hi> [I confeſs I have writ of a devout life, without being devout my ſelf; yet not without a deſire of being ſo, and it is this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire which hath given me courage to inſtruct thee: for as a great
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:121241:18"/>Learned man ſaid, To ſtudy is a good way to learn, to hear is a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, but to teach is beſt of all.] The truth is, I entertained the firſt thoughts of making theſe Dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions thus publike, whileſt I was drawing up ſomewhat for my own uſe: hoping they might do others more good then my ſelf, which might have better hearts to make uſe of them, (as indeed I ſhould oft preach with an heavy heart, were it not for hopes that many that hear me, may be more affected with what I ſpeak, then I can get my own dull ſoul to be,) but I was further en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged to this work, when I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered what an obligation it would be upon my ſelf, to the moſt earneſt endeavours in the practice of thoſe things which I have thus preſſed upon others: for if I ſhould chuſe my deviſe, it ſhould be thoſe words of the Apoſtle, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.21. Which I wiſh I could as oft ſuppoſe my ſelf
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:121241:18"/>to hear ſounding in mine ears, as <hi>Jerome</hi> did the laſt Trumpet, <hi>Thou that teacheſt another, teacheſt thou not thy ſelf?</hi> and I deſire this little Book may come into remembrance with me to ſhame me when ever I ſhall (through inadvertency or any other infirmity) ſwerve from theſe Rules my ſelf, which I have here ſet down for the uſe of others.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:121241:19"/>
            <head>THE PRACTICE OF GODLINES.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Abour to improve your acknowledged princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples concerning God.</hi> I mean ſuch princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples as are generally without diſpute, or heſitancy aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to: unleſs you think the Word of God to be a cunningly deviſed fable, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.16. or that the Kingdom of God is in word only, and not in power, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.20. that Religion is but an empty ſound, of no uſe or vertue, let your faith as the Apoſtle faith of pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, <hi>Jam.</hi> 1.4. <hi>have its perfect work,</hi> uſe it as far as it will go, and
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:121241:19"/>you ſhall find what an influence it will have upon your whole Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation. True knowledg is the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of all Religion, <hi>Jer.</hi> 22.16. <hi>Eph,</hi> 4.18. and that knowledg is not right which is not operative and ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ectuall, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 2.3, 4. Now there are three things more eſpecially, a fixed apprehenſion and ſerious conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion whereof, will be of ſingular uſe to us in all the paſſages of our lives.</p>
            <p>Firſt, The <hi>alſufficiency</hi> of God, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.1. This makes him the chief good, for this we chooſe him as our portion, and chief happineſs. Now this is the firſt ſtep which the ſoul takes towards Heaven, this goes in order before Faith, and Faith is but ſubordinate hereto, this being the act of the ſoul about our chief end; Faith reſpecting the means leading to this end. Why do we beleeve on Jeſus Chriſt? but that we may by him be brought unto God, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.18, theſe two acts are the brief a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridgment
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:121241:20"/>of the Goſpel, <hi>Acts</hi> 20.21. ſo that we ſee this is eſſentiall to Chriſtianity to take God for our chief happineſs. Now if this were but ſetled in our hearts, how would it ballaſt them and keep them ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, that they would not be toſſed up and down with the various oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currences of this life, neither lift up with <hi>proſperity,</hi> nor caſt down with <hi>adverſitys</hi> for whether we have more of theſe things they make no conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable <hi>addition</hi> to us, God is our happineſs and not the Creature; or whether we have leſs of theſe things, it is no <hi>diminution</hi> of our happineſs, we ſtill have our portion; we are but as a man that hath turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his eſtate into money, though he have not houſes, nor lands, nor flocks, nor herds; yet he hath that <hi>which anſwers all things,</hi> Eccleſ. 10.19. ſo it is with one that hath God for his portion, <hi>whoſe is the earth, and the fullneſs thereof,</hi> Hab. 3.17,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:121241:20"/>18.1 Cor. 10.28.2 Cor. 6.10. Give twenty pounds to a poor man, and you make him, take ſo much from him and you undoe him; but it is nothing in a rich mans purſe that hath thouſands coming in yearly: let an unbeliever loſe the world and he loſes all, he complains with <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ban</hi> that his gods are gone; let him have theſe things in abundance, and he is tranſported like <hi>Haman,</hi> Eſth. 5.11, 12. but theſe are ſmall things with him, whoſe portion the Lord is.</p>
            <p n="2">2. A ſecond thing which we ſhould alwayes labour for a ferious apprehenſion of, is Gods <hi>omnipre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence:</hi> by his eſſence and common providence, <hi>he is in all places,</hi> Pſal. 139.6, &amp;c. <hi>and he beholds all things that are done by the ſons of men,</hi> Heb. 4.13. but he is graciouſly preſent in a ſpeciall manner with his own peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 43.2, 5. Now to walk before God, to ſet his preſence before our eyes, doth briefly comprehend all
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:121241:21"/>Religion, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.1. <hi>Chap.</hi> 14.40.</p>
            <p n="1">1. This will awe us when we have opportunities and temptations to ſecret ſins, <hi>Gen.</hi> 39.9. The ſtory is known of <hi>Paphnutius</hi> who convert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed an <hi>Harlot</hi> by this means.</p>
            <p n="2">2. This would poſſeſs us with more <hi>reverence and godly fear in du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of Gods worſhip,</hi> 1 Cor. 11.10. If the preſence of Angels ſhould do this, much more the preſence of God.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>This will comfort us in afflict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> Pſal. 23.4, 25, 14. <hi>Encourage us againſt fears,</hi> Pſal. 16.8. yea, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke us to diligence in every good work, <hi>The eye of the maſter makes a diligent ſeruant,</hi> Col. 3.22. The A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſuppoſes, that thoſe who o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe are ſloathfull and negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent, will yet be diligent while their maſters eye is upon them.</p>
            <p n="3">3. A third thing which we ſhould alwayes ſettle in our hearts, is the <hi>univerſall providence</hi> of God, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:121241:21"/>it ſelf to every thing which comes to paſs here below, to <hi>that which is good,</hi> Gen. 31.16, 33, 5, 11. <hi>that which is evil,</hi> Iſa. 42.25. Amos 3.6. to <hi>the leaſt things,</hi> Mat. 10.28. to thoſe things which are produced by a long ſeries of ſecond cauſes, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 2.22. <hi>Gen.</hi> 45.5. to the meereſt contingencies, <hi>Pro.</hi> 16.33. Now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the occaſion which we ſhall have hereby given us to adore <hi>the perfections of God in all his works, Pſal.</hi> 8. <hi>Joh</hi> 37.14. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 107.43. we ſhall have this advantage here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, in the enjoyment of mercies.</p>
            <p>Firſt, It will teach us thankfulneſs for them, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 40.5.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Prevent our abuſe of them and teach us to uſe them for God, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 2.8. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 16.19. In afflictions this will teach us firſt to ſubmit patient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to them, as being inflicted by his <hi>authority,</hi> ordered by his wife <hi>provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence,</hi> 1 Sam. 3.18. Job 1.21. Joh. 19.11. Pſal. 46. throughout.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:121241:22"/>3. Teach us to make a right uſe of them, <hi>Mic.</hi> 6.9. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 42.25. By theſe inſtances which I have ſet down, you muy likewiſe be directed how to improve other articles of your faith.</p>
            <p>Direct. 2. <hi>What ever you do in word or deed, do all in the name of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt.</hi> This direction is in the very words of the Apoſtle, <hi>Col.</hi> 3.17. and though it be a brief dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, yet there is none that is of more generall and conſtant uſe: it is like the Carpenters rule, which he makes uſe of upon all occaſions, there is not an action of our lives wherein we have not ſome uſe here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of Now to do a thing in the name of Chriſt, imports theſe three things;</p>
            <p n="1">1. To do it by the authority of Chriſt, <hi>Mat.</hi> 21.23. <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.43. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.4.</p>
            <p n="2">2. In the power and ſtrength of Chriſt, <hi>Mark</hi> 16.17. <hi>Acts</hi> 3.12, 16. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 20.5.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:121241:22"/>3. For the ſake of Chriſt, or for his honour, <hi>Luk.</hi> 9.48. <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.20. So the <hi>Dutch Annotations</hi> on the place, and the learned <hi>Daillè</hi> in his excellent Sermon on the ſame. 1. Then let us make God of our counſell in whatever we take in hand, (This was a common practice amongſt the heathen, <hi>vatibus ſolen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne fuit nihil ſerium numine incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulto aggredi.</hi> Herbert <hi>de veritate.</hi>) <hi>Iſa.</hi> 30.1. <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 8.4. 1. Becauſe of the abſolute authority that he hath o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver us, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.21. 1 <hi>King.</hi> 18.21. 2. The dependance we have on his providence, 'tis wiſdom to make a vertue of neceſſity; if we will ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to do a thing without his <hi>mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall</hi> permiſſion, or allowance: we cannot do it without his <hi>naturall</hi> permiſſion or ſufferance, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 54.15. <hi>Jer.</hi> 42.15. <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 4.10. 3. We muſt give an account to him of our a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, he is our Judg, as well as our Lawgiver, <hi>Jam.</hi> 4.12. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.10.
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:121241:23"/>4. When we have Gods leave, we may go on with comfort, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence, <hi>Prov.</hi> 10.29. We are under his ſpeciall care and providence, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 84.11. M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Dod</hi> would ſay, he cared not where he was, if he could but anſwer theſe two queſtions well, <hi>Who am I?</hi> and <hi>what do I here?</hi> am I a Child of God? and am I in my way? if we were carefull of the diſcharge of our duty, we might free our ſelves from all other care; but as it is the humour of every man naturally, to look more after other mens affairs then his own; ſo we deal after the ſame manner with God, we buſie our ſelves about <hi>his work,</hi> the event and ſucceſs of our affairs, which belong to his provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence to order and direct: and in the mean while neglect <hi>our own du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> leaving that to God, uſually up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on pretence of the neceſſity of his determining grace, which doth no more make void our endeavours in
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:121241:23"/>
               <hi>ſpirituall</hi> actions, then the neceſſity of the concurrence of his generall providence in our <hi>naturall</hi> actions.</p>
            <p>Now for knowing the mind of God in what we go about, we have his Word to direct us. In particular caſes where we have no expreſs rule for our direction, our end muſt di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect us, the edification of ſouls, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.23. and the glory of God, (of which more afterwards;) beſides God doth by his providence ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, and ſometimes by making ſtrong impreſſions upon the will, <hi>Acts</hi> 20.22. give ſome hints of his mind, <hi>vide Valdeſſo Conſid.</hi> 25. but to be ſure we muſt make the former our chief rules to guid us, and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low theſe laſt, only when the Word is not clear, and where neither of thoſe mentioned ends which we ſhould propound to our ſelves, do turn the ballance, but it remains ſtill equally poyſed: otherwiſe we may take the violent inclinations of our
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:121241:24"/>own luſts, for an impreſſion of the ſpirit, and a temptation for a lead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing providence, <hi>Deut.</hi> 13.3. See 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 24.5, 6, 7.</p>
            <p n="2">II. What we do we ſhould do in the ſtrength of Chriſt, waiting upon him for the concurrence of his ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall providence in our ordinary, naturall, and civil actions, <hi>James</hi> 4.15. of his more ſpeciall providence in extraordinary actions, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 17.45. 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 14.11. and of his ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall grace in ſpirituall actions, <hi>Eph.</hi> 6.10. <hi>Phil</hi> 4.13. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.1. So that we ſhould <hi>commit all our wayes unto the Lord,</hi> Prov. 16.3. venturing up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on nothing in our <hi>practiſes,</hi> which we dare not commend to God, for a bleſſing in our <hi>prayers;</hi> our ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary affairs, we may commit to him by a generall recommendation in our daily prayers: extraordinary af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs by a more particular ſolemn addreſſing our ſelves to him, <hi>Gen.</hi> 32.10. <hi>Neh.</hi> 1.4. <hi>Eſth.</hi> 4.16. ſudden
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:121241:24"/>emergencies, by ſhort ſecret eja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culations, <hi>Neh.</hi> 2.4. This practice would make us deſiſt from many raſh undertakings: we many times unadviſedly ruſhing upon thoſe things which we ſhould not have a face to own before God in prayer: as the poor man when he had ſtol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len a Lamb for the neceſſities of his family, when having made it ready, he came (as his manner was) to pray for a bleſſing upon it, his heart ſmote him, ſo that he could have no peace till he went and acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his ſin, and made a promiſe of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution.</p>
            <p n="3">III. We ſhould do all for the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of Chriſt, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.32. 1. This is the ultimate end of all things, <hi>Pro.</hi> 16.4. <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.36. 2. Though the purity of the end will not correct they ciouſneſs of the means, as the popiſh Caſuiſts teach; yet it will ſanctifie all our naturall and civill actions, adopting them as it were
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:121241:25"/>into the number of religious acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and inſcribing them with holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to the Lord, <hi>Zach.</hi> 14.21. <hi>Col.</hi> 3.23, 24.</p>
            <p>The pooreſt ſervant by diſcharg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his duty in a right manner, and directing his intention aright, may in the meaneſt employment ſerve Jeſus Chriſt, and with confidence expect his reward from him. Of the univerſall influence that a right di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of our intentions hath upon our whole practice, See <hi>Bacons Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayes</hi> 57. and <hi>Richeomes Adieu de l' Ame devote Devis</hi> 59.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Without this our ſpirituall actions are not good, <hi>Zach.</hi> 7.7.</p>
            <p n="4">4. This will preſcribe a right manner and meaſure to all our law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full actions. I mean ſuch as are in themſelves lawfull, as eating, drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, recreations, and ſuch like: <hi>finis dat modum &amp; menſuram medits.</hi> And herein Chriſtians had need to be very circumſpect, becauſe they
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:121241:25"/>ſin moſt frequently in ſuch actions, <hi>licitis perimus omnes,</hi> it is ſaid of the old world, <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.38. that <hi>they were eating, drinking, marrying, and giving in marriage;</hi> there was no hurt in theſe actions, if they had ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved a due ſeaſon, manner, and meaſure in them. Chriſtians ſtartle at ſuch things as ſwearing, lying, ſtealing, adultery, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but in the uſe of things lawfull, they are more ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure, and ſo do more eaſily ſlide into a ſinfull exceſs.</p>
            <p n="5">5. This will direct us (as was before hinted) where our way is doubtfull. Where we have expreſs commands, or prohibitions in the Word of God, our way is plain, there is no queſtion to be made, but in many caſes our actions are not determined by any particular direct command, but are left to be guided by Chriſtian prudence; now in ſuch a caſe, our end will be of much uſe to guid us; as a man that is to draw a
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:121241:26"/>line, if he have no rule to make it by, he oft caſts his eye upon that term, or point to which it is to be drawn; or if a man have a way to go, and there be no beaten path, if he can ſee the place which he is to go to, his way is to aime at that, and make ſtraight over towards it: ſo when a caſe is doubtfull, we ſhould fix our eye upon the glory of God, and ſee which way hath the moſt direct tendency thereto, and take that way. Now though we cannot alwayes have an <hi>actuall</hi> intention of the glory of God, yet we ſhould <hi>ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitually</hi> intend it, and the more we can <hi>actually</hi> intend it the better; eſpecially in ſuch actions as are of moment in the courſe of our lives, we ſhould renew our actuall inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and (as was ſaid before) when a caſe is doubtfull, we ſhould fix our eye upon this end; as a man that is travelling towards a place, ſuppoſe to <hi>London,</hi> he doth not actually
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:121241:26"/>think on the place which he goes to every ſtep he takes, but if he come to a place where there are two wayes, then he bethinks himſelf of the place which he is going to, that he may take that way which is more likely to lead him thereto.</p>
            <p>And if any ask now how our na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall or civill actions conduce to the glory of God? I anſwer;</p>
            <p>Firſt, They may be done to the glory of God, in reſpect of the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of them, when we uſe ſuch mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, holy fear, heavenly mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs in theſe actions, that every one may ſee holineſs written upon them, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.1. <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.10. when we obſerve not a Chriſtian <hi>decorum</hi> in our naturall and civill actions, it is a diſhonour to our profeſſion; <hi>Editur quantum eſurientes cupiunt,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>We eat</hi> (<hi>ſaith</hi> Tertullian <hi>of the Chriſtians,</hi>) <hi>as much as is neceſſary to ſatisfie ones appetite; we drink as much as is permitted to Chriſtians
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:121241:27"/>that have a care of their purity; they that ſit there take their refreſhment with ſuch temperance, as they may remember they are obliged to worſhip God at night,</hi> Apol. cap. 39.</p>
            <p>Secondly, In reſpect of their ul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timate tendency, they may be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervient to the glory of God, though they have not ſuch an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate connexion therewith, as when we uſe diligence in our par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular callings, that we may have wherewith to ſupply the neceſſities of others, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.28. to provide for thoſe belonging to our own charge, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.8. that we may with the more freedom wait upon God, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing exempted from perplexing cares, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.35. that we may be freed from the temptations of po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verty, and may not be burdenſome to others, <hi>Prov.</hi> 30.9. 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.11. So when we <hi>ſtudy for this end, that we may excell for the edifying of the Church,</hi> 1 Cor. 14.12. When we eat,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:121241:27"/>drink, uſe recreations that our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies may be ſtrengthened, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 10.17. that ſo they may be the more fit to ſerve the ſoul in its operations, that we may by both ſoul and body be more fit to honour God in our places; ſo in our civil viſits, we ſhould conſider what they will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute to our chief end, what op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity we may have of doing or receiving good; how far our Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian profeſſion requires this of us, that <hi>we may ſhew all gentleneſs to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards all men,</hi> Tit. 3.2. <hi>and add to brotherly kindneſs charity,</hi> 2 Pet. 1.7.</p>
            <p>Direct. 3. <hi>Prize all oportunities of communion with God in his Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances;</hi> ſuch as Prayer, reading and hearing the Word, Chriſtian pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence muſt alot the time for theſe, according to our occaſions, oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ies, neceſſities, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 42.1, 2. &amp; 63.1, 2. &amp; 84.1, 2. &amp; 122.1.</p>
            <p>Firſt, They are our <hi>duty,</hi> part of that homage which we owe to God,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:121241:28"/>as our Lord and Lawgiver, by pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to acknowledg our dependance on him, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 65.2. and our ſubje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to him by ſitting down at his feet to receive the Law from his mouth, to take our inſtruction from him, <hi>Deut.</hi> 33.3.</p>
            <p>Secondly, They are our <hi>privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges,</hi> which coſt two of the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt gifts which Heaven could afford, <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.17. <hi>The Son of God, that we might have acceptance, the Spirit of God that we might have aſſiſtance;</hi> what greater priviledg are we ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of, then at any time to go and <hi>reveal our cauſe to God,</hi> Ier. 20.21. to <hi>caſe our complaints before him,</hi> to have leave to beg <hi>any thing of him,</hi> Ioh. 15.8. Luk. 11.13. to <hi>ask sounſell of him,</hi> Pſal. 119.24. eſpecially when his Word is the miniſtration of the Spirit, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.6. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.2. there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in our communion with God a transfuſion of ſpirits, he communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cating his Spirit or divine nature to
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:121241:28"/>us therein, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.18. beſides our own preſſing neceſſities which ſhould daily provoke us hereto: <hi>the oftner we come to God the more welcome,</hi> Cant. 2.14. Jer. 2.32. and the more boldneſs and liberty of acceſs we ſhall have, diſuſe and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frequency breeding a ſtrangeneſs betwixt God and the ſoul, and deading the heart to communion with him.</p>
            <p>Direct. 4. <hi>Be very ſerious in the performance of holy duties;</hi> be care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to joyn therein <hi>attention of mind.</hi> Ezek. 33.32. <hi>ſincerity of heart,</hi> Pſal. 145.18. <hi>intenſion of affictions,</hi> Rom. 12.11. Acts 27.7. <hi>and holy fear and reverence,</hi> Heb. 12.28. Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians are very faulty in this parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular; for beſides their rude irreve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent behaviour in holy duties, when the beſt ſupply that we can make to the defect of our prayers, (after our hearts have been roving and wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering therein, notwithſtanding the
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:121241:29"/>ſtricteſt hand that we can keep over them,) is by recollection of all the ſtrength of our ſouls to enforce them by an hearty <hi>Amen.</hi> You ſhall have men off their knees, (if ever they were on them) or ready to run away from the duty when it grows towards an end, as if they were glad that ſuch a task were done. Verily I have oft wondered how ſuch pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaneſs in divine worſhip ſhould be conſiſtent with the <hi>fear of God,</hi> and yet been loath to condemn thoſe that are guilty of it. I can ſcarce think of this but I am in <hi>Pauls</hi> caſe, <hi>Acts</hi> 17.16. for (as <hi>Mirandula</hi> ſaith in another caſe, That its a wonder that any ſhould doubt of the truth of the Goſpel after ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny proofs of it, but a greater won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that any ſhould believe it and live as if it were not true, <hi>Ep.</hi> 1. <hi>ad Nepot.</hi> So it is a wonder that any ſhould be ſo bruitiſh as to worſhip a falſe god, but a greater wonder,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:121241:29"/>that any worſhiping the true God, ſhould worſhip him as if he were no God. We ought to give the more diligent heed herein, becauſe there is the ſame time ſpent in the ſlight performance of duties, which is ſpent in a right performance of them; and a man had better ſow his ground with good ſeed though it coſt him dear, then with darnell or cockle, though he can have it for nothing: and as we loſe the fruit of our duties, and anſwer of our pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers when we are ſlight in them, ſo we loſe the ſweetneſs that is to be had in communion with God in them, and that is the reaſon we come with ſuch dead hearts to du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties; and we had need be watchfull herein, becauſe Satan is very buſie to interrupt us in holy duties, <hi>Luk.</hi> 8.12. <hi>Zach.</hi> 3.1. and our own hearts are very apt to wander therein. <hi>Ben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard</hi> ſadly complains of this in his Meditations, <hi>cap.</hi> 8. and <hi>de demo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teriori,</hi>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:121241:30"/>cap. 29, &amp; 33. how he ſcarce could attend to his own prayers, or mind what he ſaid in them himſelf, and ſo loſt the fruit of them: See <hi>Dike</hi> on the Heart, <hi>cap.</hi> 21. <hi>Cyprian de Orat. Dom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now for our help therein, let us firſt conſider the nature of God with whom we have to do; he is a great King, and his Name is dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, <hi>Mal.</hi> 1.14. read that Chapter throughout, he will not bear it to be put off with ſlight ſervices, he will have none of his work done <hi>negligently,</hi> Jer. 48.10. he will be <hi>ſanctified of all ſuch as draw nigh to him</hi> Lev. 10.3. he will be <hi>ſerved with fear and trembling,</hi> Pſal. 2.11. trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling at the Word of God is the Character of a godly man, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 66.2, 4. <hi>Ezra</hi> 10.3.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Let us conſider the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the ſervices wherein we have to do with him, and we may conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der them under a threefold notion:
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:121241:30"/>Firſt, as <hi>duties;</hi> this will lay an awe upon our conſciences, and keep us to a due conſtant obſervance of them; it is dangerous to free our conſciences from this obligation, by laying aſide the opinion of duty, for we ſee by experience how eaſily men are tempted to a neglect of thoſe things which they look upon as only matter of liberty, and not as neceſſary duty. 2. Let us conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der them as <hi>priviledges:</hi> this will keep us from that wearineſs which is ready to grow upon us in them, while we conſider them only as bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denſome tasks, <hi>Mal.</hi> 1.13.</p>
            <p>And from reſting in the <hi>work done,</hi> which we ſhall be apt to do if we look upon them only as duties.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Let us conſider them as <hi>Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lents</hi> which we muſt give an account of, for ſo they are if we look upon them as means of grace, <hi>Luk.</hi> 12.48. this will quicken us up to more earneſt diligence in the improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:121241:31"/>of them. And for prayer in particular let me add this one word, whenever we draw nigh to God in it, let us but conſider what it is, or what we are about, <hi>viz The making our requeſts known to God, by prayer and ſupplication with thanksgiving, Phil.</hi> 4.6. that ſo we may be furniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with expreſſions, not from our <hi>heads,</hi> but from our <hi>hearts;</hi> that our words may not be fetched from our memories or inventions, but from our reall deſires and inward affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions.</p>
            <p>Direct. 5. <hi>Be very carefull net to neglect known duties:</hi> We uſe to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve in polemicall Divinity, that the plaineſt truths are leaſt ſtudied, becauſe they are taken for granted, and ſo men think they need not bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie themſelvts about them. I wiſh we could not make the like obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in practicall Divinity, though there is not the like reaſon for the neglect of the <hi>practice</hi> that there is
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:121241:31"/>of the <hi>ſtudy</hi> of thoſe things which we know, <hi>the end of knowledg is pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice,</hi> Deut. 29.29. But ſo it is uſual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that men are very inquiſitive into thoſe things which are doubtfull, as if they wanted matter for the exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of their zeal, or as if they would complement with God as they ſometimes do with men, telling him in effect that they do but wait for an opportunity to ſerve him, when they overlook ordinary acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged duties; like the Jews, which were very forward to enquire whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they ſhould faſt as they had done formerly, and in the mean while they neglected the duties of morality, <hi>Mic.</hi> 6.7. the greateſt queſtioniſts are many times the leaſt doers, but as <hi>Luther</hi> would ſay, <hi>God loves not Quaeriſtas, but Curriſtas,</hi> not ſuch as will be alwayes enqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, but ſuch as will be active or doing: if you would know more of the mind of God in things that are
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:121241:32"/>doubtfull, do more of what you al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready know, <hi>Joh.</hi> 7.17. Mind what is your preſent duty, what is the next ſtep you are to take in the way to Heaven, as the <hi>evil</hi> of the day, ſo the <hi>duty</hi> of the day is ſufficient for it.</p>
            <p>Direct. 6. <hi>Labour to know the true bounds of your Christian liberty.</hi> Not that you may walk to the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt extent of it, for the ſatisfying of your naturall deſires, nor that you may for any carnall intereſt baſely comply with mens humours; but yet there may be great uſe of this, both in reſpect of our ſelves and others: men do oft lay unneceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary burdens upon themſelves, binding themſelves (where God hath looſed them) to their own great prejudice, like thoſe 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.7. inſtances whereof are very obvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous. I would not interpret that place <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 7.16. in favour of luke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warmneſs, or to allay mens zeal with the baſe mixture of carnall policy:
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:121241:32"/>yet doubtleſs men do ſometimes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy themſelves by too much opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nionativeneſs and ſelf-conceit, or over-rigidly inſiſting on ſome things where God allows them a greater latitude. See D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Reynolds</hi> on this place, in his moſt excellent Commentary on <hi>Eccleſiaſtes</hi> in the larger Engliſh <hi>Annotations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But Chriſtians do uſually moſt wrong others hereby: Firſt, In judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them, and caſting them out of their charity for thoſe things which they have liberty in, or which they may lawfully do: <hi>strong Chriſtians are not more ready to deſpiſe the weak, then the weak are to judg the ſtrong,</hi> Rom. 14.3. and I know not which is the greater ſin; the former for the moſt part is worſe in reſpect of its principle from whence it proceeds, but the latter in reſpect of the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of it. But ſecondly, We further wrong others, in that we do not leave our ſelves a liberty where God
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:121241:33"/>hath left it us, for accommodating our ſelves to them, and pleaſing them <hi>for their good to edification;</hi> or as others have it, <hi>in that which is good;</hi> where we have the true bounds ſet to man-pleaſing, for the matter it muſt be in that which <hi>is good,</hi> we muſt not pleaſe their ſinfull humours, or comply with their cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt luſts. Then there muſt be a right end, it muſt be for <hi>their edifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation,</hi> Rom. 15.2. and this rule the Apoſtle himſelf put in practice, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.19. <hi>Chap.</hi> 10.33.</p>
            <p>Direct. 7. <hi>Labour to make the beſt improvement of your time.</hi> The Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle indeed exhorts to <hi>redeem time, Eph.</hi> 5.16. which is an expreſſion of doubtfull ſignification, and capable of various interpretations; but in propriety of ſpeech, time that is loſt is not to be redeemed; we cannot poſſibly recover miſpent time; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deeming time is alike impoſſible as merit, <hi>Luk.</hi> 17.10. becauſe all that
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:121241:33"/>we can do in our time is our duty; and it is not in <hi>morals</hi> as in <hi>natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals,</hi> where by reſting one hour we are able to work more vigorouſly another, but the more remiſs we are, the greater indiſpoſition we bring upon our ſelves. If a man ſuffer weeds to grow in his field; though he pluck them up before they ſeed, or ſpoyl his corn, yet he loſes ſo much ground as they grow upon: ſo though God ſhould par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don the miſpending of our time, yet we ſhall loſe the fruit of what we might have (in that time) <hi>ſown to the Spirit:</hi> and as good husbands will loſe none of their ground, but have every parcell bring them forth ſomething, ſo we ſhould endeavour that every parcell of our time may be ſown with ſome ſeed of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs; yea, we ſhould make ſome improvement of that time in which we do the works of our particular callings to ſome ſpirituall advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:121241:34"/>(if our imployments be ſuch as exerciſe the hand and not the head) by ſome uſefull meditations; as ſome will plant their hedg-rowes with fruit trees, reckoning that what they get thereby is clear gain, becauſe they take up no room which might be put to any other uſe; ſo what we get by ſuch medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations is clearly gained, becauſe it doth not hinder any other imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. But as it is not enough for the husbandman to ſow all his ground, but he muſt obſerve what agrees beſt with this or that grain, and as it is not ſufficient that he be alwayes employed, unleſs he obſerve the due ſeaſon for his ſeverall affairs, ſo it is not ſufficient that we be alwayes doing that which is materially good, but there muſt be a prudent choice of the fitteſt ſeaſon for every action, for <hi>there is for every purpoſe a time and judgment, therefore is the miſery of man great upon him,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:121241:34"/>ſome few men have the wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome <hi>to know time and judgment.</hi> Eccl. 8.5, 6. but he is the bleſſed man, that <hi>brings forth fruit in its ſeaſon,</hi> Pſal. 1.3. Yet let not your <hi>ſouls enter into the ſecrets</hi> of thoſe, who ſeeming to themſelves to have a perfect underſtanding of the times and ſeaſons wherein the things foretold in Scripture ſhall have their accompliſhment, think themſelves bound to attempt ſuch things as they ſuppoſe may be help<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to the bringing forth of that which divine providence ſeems to be travelling with, calling this <hi>the work of the day, or of their genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> The good man <hi>Moſes</hi> ran into this miſtake, but he was glad to flee for it, and keep ſheep fourty years, till he had a more cleer call from God, to undertake that work which he before knew God had deſigned him for, <hi>Acts</hi> 7.23, &amp;c. More parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly let us endeavour to improve
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:121241:35"/>our time well when we are in <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany,</hi> and when we are <hi>alone,</hi> for <hi>ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety</hi> and <hi>ſolitude</hi> ſhare our time. Firſt, In company, let us labour to do good or to get good, at leaſt that we do no hurt nor receive any: and to that end, avoid (as much as may be) the ſociety of thoſe with whom we are like neither to do or receive good, and thoſe are ſuch as are pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane ſcorners, and ſuch as are meerly carnall, and are much our ſuperiours. And when you are in company, make conſcience of your words; 1. Becauſe we are very apt to offend in them, <hi>Jam.</hi> 3.2, 6. We may complain of moſt mens diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes as <hi>Bernard Apolog. ad Guil. Abbat. Nihil de Scripturis nihil de ſalute agitur animarum, ſed nugae &amp; riſus &amp; verbae proferuntur in ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum;</hi> they are all froth and vanity, there is nothing in them of the Scripture, or of the ſalvation of mens ſouls. <hi>Ita fabulantur ut qui
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:121241:35"/>ſciant Dominum audire,</hi> ſaith <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullian</hi> of the ancient Chriſtians, <hi>Apol. cap.</hi> 39. they ſo talk as thoſe who know that God hears them. So <hi>Pſal.</hi> 139.4. Remember the ſtory of him that heard a pen writing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind the curtain while he was under examination, which made him look more narrowly to his words. 2. There is ſpeciall <hi>notice taken of them,</hi> Mal. 3.16. And 3. <hi>We muſt give an account of them,</hi> Mat. 12.36, 37. and that we may never want matter of uſefull diſcourſe, let us alwayes be furniſhed with ſome profitable queſtions to propound, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 10.1, &amp;c. which we may be ſupplied with, either from what we hear or read daily of the Word of God, or ſome paſſages of Gods Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence, or our own experience, and this will be uſefull both to our ſelves and others, we may hereby increaſe our own knowledg, and give others occaſion for imploying
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:121241:36"/>their Talents, which many times lye wrapped up uſeleſs, either through too much reſervedneſs or ſlowneſs of ſpeech, or an over-awing mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty, or becauſe men know not ſo well how to ſuit their diſcourſes to the conditions and capacities of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers: and it will not be altogether in vain to propound queſtions to thoſe that are our equals or below us in underſtanding. We may like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe take occaſion from ordinary occurrences to raiſe ſpirituall diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes, which was Chriſts uſuall practice, <hi>Joh.</hi> 4.10, 6, 26. but it is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver neceſſary that we obſerve the tempers, faculties, abilities, capaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, conditions of thoſe with whom we have to do? that we may accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modate our ſelves (as far as may be) thereunto; this will render our ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety more acceptable to others, more profitable both to others and our ſelves. By obſerving mens tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers we may the more eaſily inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuate
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:121241:36"/>what we pleaſe into them: by obſerving their faculties and abili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, we may both pleaſe them and profit our ſelves: becauſe men love to diſcourſe of things belonging to their own faculties, or wherein their abilities chiefly lye, and about thoſe things we may expect the moſt ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfying anſwers from them, if they be ſuch things as may be any ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage to us to know: if we ſuit our diſcourſes to mens conditions, it will add much <hi>grace and comeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to our ſpeech,</hi> Prov. 15.23. &amp; 25.11. but if we do not in all things ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply our ſelves to mens capacities, we ſhall but weary them, and what we labour to pour into them will run beſide, <hi>Joh.</hi> 16.12. <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.1. But re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member ſtill to be <hi>ſwift to hear, ſlow to ſpeak,</hi> Jam. 1.19. to <hi>ſhew all meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs towards all men, to speak evil of none,</hi> unleſs you be called thereto, <hi>Tit.</hi> 3.2. to be ſparing of your pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, and as ſparing of your ſecrets,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:121241:37"/>unles to ſuch, whoſe faithfullneſs you have good experience of, or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les they leave as much in pawn with you as you truſt with them: for by imparting our ſecrets to others, we oft put our ſelves into their power, ſo that they have a check upon us, according to that, <hi>Scire volunt ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creta domus atque inde timeri,</hi> Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven. Sat. 13.</p>
            <p>And laſtly, Joyn prudence with innocence, that you may neither do wrong nor receive any, <hi>Mat</hi> 10.16. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 101.2.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Labour to ſpend your time well when you are alone; <hi>Take heed to your ſpirits,</hi> Mal. 2.17. there is the <hi>beginning of all miſchief,</hi> Mat. 15.19. then is the ſeaſon for Satan to come and deal with us about his works of darkneſs, which he hath to put us upon, therefore we ſhould prevent him by ſome good and profitable exerciſe; if <hi>David</hi> had taken this courſe, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 11. how much evill
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:121241:37"/>might it have prevented? how much work have we lying upon our hands to take up every ſpare minute of our lives? how many things are we ignorant of, which we may imploy our ſolitary time about, in inform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our ſelves by reading the Word of God, or uſing the help of others, which we have ready at hand in ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h abundance? or if we cannot read the Scriptures, or ſome other good books, as in a journey, or in our beds in the night, how much work have we to do upon our hearts? How many affections to quicken by holy meditation? how many doubts to reſolve, and queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to anſwer concerning our own ſpiritual condition by ſelf-examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion? And for your help in theſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſes,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Labour to have the <hi>Word of God dwelling richly in you,</hi> Prov. 6.12. Mat. 12.35.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Have this good treaſure in
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:121241:38"/>your heart diſpoſed into ſome or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, when our thoughts lie on a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed heap, we cannot ſo eaſily find out what we have occaſion to uſe, let us ſometimes <hi>look upward to God,</hi> conſider his Nature, his Attributes, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 104.34. his Wiſdom, Goodnes, Power, Faithfulneſs, which he hath proclaimed in his Word, manifeſted in his Works, eſpecially in that work of his manifold Wiſdom, which is the ſubject of Angels meditation, <hi>Eph.</hi> 3.10.1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.11. Sometimes he <hi>looking backward on the wayes of Gods providence toward you,</hi> Pſ. 139.8, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 2 Sam. 22.1, <hi>&amp;c. or your ways towards God,</hi> 1 Tim. 1.13. Sometimes <hi>look downwards into your own hearts,</hi> ſee what work of God you can find there, what remainders of ſin are ſtil there. Sometimes <hi>look forward to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards your end,</hi> Meditate on Death, Judgment, Heaven, Hell. So there are other <hi>uſefull Subjects,</hi> as the love of God, the excellency of
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:121241:38"/>Chriſt, the vanity of the World, the ſinfulneſs of ſin, the deceit fulneſs of the heart, which Chriſtians of ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary capacities that are acquainted with the Scriptures, and uſe to hear Sermons, may eaſily improve by Meditation to the quickning of their affections, and ſtrengthening their reſolutions, and make your choice of theſe Subjects to meditate on according to your preſent ſtate; as in proſperity oft be thinking of ſuch things as may keep your hearts low, as your former condition, and Gods gracious providence in raiſing you up, if your condition have for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly been worſe, <hi>Gen.</hi> 32.10.2 <hi>Sa.</hi> 7.18. however of the vanity of the creature, the brevity of life, the joys of Heaven, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in adverſity chooſe ſuch matter of Meditation, as may be moſt fit to work you to patience and contentedneſs, <hi>Mic.</hi> 7.9. <hi>Ezr.</hi> 9.13. and then alſo <hi>make diligent ſearch into your own hearts and ways,</hi>
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:121241:39"/>to find out what may probably be the cauſe of Gods contending with you, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 77.6. <hi>Job</hi> 10.2. &amp; 34.31, 32.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Raiſe up matter of holy Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation from earthly things; God hath done much for our help in this exerciſe, by holding forth heavenly myſteries in his Word, in ſimilitudes taken from earthly things, ſo, that almoſt every creature, every action may ſuggeſt ſome uſeful Meditation to us; if we be travelling, if we ſee a pleaſant way, and much company, we do not conſider theſe things, but what way it is that leads to the place we go to; ſo though <hi>the way of ſin be pleaſant to the fleſh, and most walk in it,</hi> Mat. 7.13, 14. that ſhould be no temptation to us, becauſe that doth not lead to Heaven whither we go. If we meet with bad lodging or mean entertainment at our Inn, we know it is but for a night, and we ſhall have better when we come to our journeys end, ſo though we
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:121241:39"/>have but bad entertainment in this world, we are but ſtrangers, this is but our Inne, we ſhall be better ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodated when we come to thoſe <hi>Manſions which Chriſt is gone before to prepare for us,</hi> Joh. 14.2. The like Meditations may be raiſed from moſt occurrences of our life.</p>
            <p>Direct. 8. <hi>Let us continually ſet before us the perfect patern of our Lord Jeſus.</hi> We are more eaſily led by examples than precepts, and Chriſt is the only perfect patern; o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers are to be followed ſo far only as they follow him, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.1.</p>
            <p>Not that all the actions of Chriſt are imitable; he was not meer man, but God alſo, and Mediatour be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt God and Man; and what he did as God, or as Mediator we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not imitate him in; but there are di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers things wherein the Scripture propounds his examples to us for imitation, as</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Love,</hi> Eph. 5.1, 2. 1 Joh. 3.16.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:121241:40"/>2. <hi>Meekneſs and Humility,</hi> Mat. 11.29. Joh. 13.14. Rom. 15.3.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Self-denial,</hi> Mat. 16.24. Phil. 2.3, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 2 Cor. 8.9.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Patience,</hi> 1 Pet. 2.21.</p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>Making it his work to do good, Act.</hi> 10.38. And theſe are graces which carry a great ſtroak in all the paſſages of our lives.</p>
            <p>Now the example of Chriſt doth not only ſerve for our direction, ſo as we ſhould oft think with our ſelves in the conduct and manage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the affairs of our life, what Chriſt himſelf would do, or how he would carry himſelf in ſuch a caſe, were he upon earth again as former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that we may behave our ſelves after the ſame manner. But 2. It may be for our encouragement; he is of a mean, baſe ſpirit, that will not follow where his General leads; <hi>Malus miles eſt qui imperatorem ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens ſequitur.</hi> Sen. <hi>Ep.</hi> 107. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Cato</hi> when he was to lead his
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:121241:40"/>ſouldiers through a place of danger and difficulty, told them he would go before them, and they ſhould not ſee him drink while they were thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty, nor take his eaſe while they were weary, nor ſee any thing in him which ſhould difference him at all from a common ſouldier, <hi>Lucan. l.</hi> 9. So Chriſt may ſay to us, <hi>He took upon him the meanest condition,</hi> Phil. 2.6. there is nothing which he calls us to ſuffer, but he hath ſuffered worſe for us, why ſhould not we then <hi>take up our croſs and go after him?</hi> Yea, 2. after his ſuffering he was <hi>crown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with glory,</hi> Heb. 12.2, 3. So, <hi>If we ſuffer with him, we ſhall alſo be glorified with him,</hi> Rom. 8.17. Mat. 19.28.</p>
            <p>Direct. 9. <hi>Every night take an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of the paſſages of the day paſt. Vid.</hi> Bald. <hi>de conſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ient. l.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 2. <hi>caſ.</hi> 2. Examine your ſelves, how you have obſerved the fore-mentioned rules, what the conſtant frame of your
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:121241:41"/>heart hath been, what you have done, upon what grounds, whether it have been with the warrant of Gods Word, for what end, whether it hath had any tendency to the glory of God, and ſubſerviency to your chief end; whether that hath been in your intention; what op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunities you have neglected of communion with God, what hath been the carriage of your heart in holy duties, how you have behaved your ſelves in company, what good you have done, whether any have been the better for you, or you for them, what you have taken into <hi>the good treaſure of your hearts, and what you have laid out,</hi> Mat. 12.35. what temper your heart hath been in when alone: and ſo you may go over the ſeveral paſſages of the day. Hereby you will always be in ſome good preparation for death, it will not ſurprize you wholly unready, when you daily caſt up your ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:121241:41"/>you will be better acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with your own ſpiritual eſtate, you will ſee what progreſs you make in the way towards Heaven, what ground you gain of your cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions, where Satan hath moſt advantage againſt you, what ſinne you are moſt frequently overtaken with, what is the weakeſt place of your ſoul; you will likewiſe be kept hereby from lying long in any ſinne unrepented of: if <hi>David</hi> had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly obſerved this courſe, he had never lien ſo long as he did in carnal ſecurity; you may likewiſe do well to take ſpecial notice of the paſſages of Gods providence towards you. And to keep a record or journal of the more remarkable paſſages of your lives, is a practice commended by divers godly men from their own experience. For direction wherein, ſee M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>White</hi> in his Treatiſe of the <hi>Power of Godlineſs,</hi> and M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Bedle</hi> in his <hi>Diary of a thankefull Chriſtian.</hi>
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:121241:42"/>And further this review of Gods dealings with you, and your carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age towards him, will furniſh you with matter of confeſſion, petition, thankſgiving, and put you upon the freſh exerciſe of your faith, and renewing your hold on Jeſus Chriſt in your Evening Prayers.</p>
            <p>Direct. 10. <hi>Awake with God in the Morning.</hi> I have diſpoſed of this Rule here, becauſe of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendance which it hath on that which goeth before: This was <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vids</hi> practice, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 139.17 18. How precious are thy thoughts, <hi>i.e.</hi> the thoughts which I have of thee; the affix in the Hebrew Notes oft the Object, and not the Subject, as <hi>Gen.</hi> 16.5. <hi>Jer.</hi> 32.40.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>God viſits us every morning, Job</hi> 7.18. <hi>Lam.</hi> 3.23.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Then our hearts are fitteſt for heavenly Meditation, when our ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits are refreſhed, and our hearts have not yet been intangled with
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:121241:42"/>the things of the world.</p>
            <p n="3">3. If holy thoughts do not firſt take place, Satan will ſoon thruſt in. <hi>Our hearts are</hi> (as <hi>Bernard</hi> ſaith) <hi>like a mill that grinds every thing that is put upon it, whether good or bad, Med. devot. eap.</hi> 10. See there how he complains of the ſad effect of giving way to evil thoughts, how his heart was thereby eſtranged from the love of heavenly things.</p>
            <p n="4">4. This is neceſſary for getting our hearts into a right frame, for walking with God all the day: if we would have our watch go right all the day, we muſt wind it up in the morning; ſo we had need to wind up our hearts every morning, if we would <hi>order our converſation aright.</hi> 1. Then let us meditate on the goodneſs of God towards us particularly the night paſt, our pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection, preſervation, refreſhment that God ſhould think of us, when we cannot think of him, take care of
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:121241:43"/>us, when we can take none of our ſelves, watch over us while we ſleep, keep us from ſleeping the ſleep of death; and bethink your ſelves, what thanks you ſhould render to the Lord for his gracious dealings with you; and how you may return the uſe of that life to him, which he reſtores to you every Morning. And to this end. 2. Review the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count which you took of your ſelvs the night before: See wherein it was that you was moſt eaſily over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken, where Satan got an advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage againſt you, whether you were not ready to offend with your tongue in company, whether your heart did not ſteal from you in holy duties, whether vain thoughts did not devour the time of your ſoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, what baits you found your hearts moſt ready to riſe to, what are the uſual out-goings of your hearts, what evil haunts they have; whether pride and vain-glory, ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuality,
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:121241:43"/>raſh anger, peeviſhneſs, impatience, or what other ſin hath the greateſt advantage againſt you: and conſider, what temptations you are lik to meet with that day, which may moſt endanger you; and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving found out the <hi>plague of your own hearts,</hi> 3. Furniſh your ſelves with the ſtrongeſtarguments againſt ſuch a ſin, (which you may gather up as you meet with them in your hearing or reading) and inforce them upon your own ſouls, by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muning with your hearts, till you have brought your ſelves to ſome fixed reſolutions of <hi>cleaving to the Lord,</hi> Act. 11.23. Pſal. 119.106. Some adviſe us for the confirming our reſolutions, to lay ſome penal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty upon our ſelves every time we fail of making them good. Of which you may ſee ſeveral inſtances in <hi>Drexelius</hi> his <hi>Triſmegiſtus Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anus,</hi> lib. 1. cap. 6. But although ſome of them ſavour too much of
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:121241:44"/>Popiſh Superſtition, yet godly ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row doth work an holy revenge, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.11. which we may take up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on our ſelves, by denying our ſelves the uſe of our lawfull liberty in thoſe things wherein we have abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed it, or wherein we are in danger again to abuſe it, if we ſhould take it: and watching our own hearts, as we would watch a thief, when we are caſt upon ſuch temptations, as we have formerly been eaſily en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſnared by, <hi>Prov.</hi> 23.1, 2. 4. Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving by the fore-mentioned Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations brought our hearts to ſome fixed reſolutions; let us not truſt to our own purpoſes, but in the next place, go to God, in whom we have both <hi>ſtrength and righteouſneſs,</hi> Iſa. 45.24. and <hi>commit the keeping of our ſouls to him in well-doing,</hi> 1 Pet. 4.19. And as we may be furniſhed with matter for our prayers in the evening, from the account which we take of our ſelves, ſo in the
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:121241:44"/>morning from our early Meditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and that is the reaſon why I have not (as many others that write exerciſes of devotion) either ſet down any form of Prayer, or dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted you to any, he will not need any form of Prayer that practices theſe duties, to lead his affections, or teach him to expreſs his deſires before God in ſecret; and for fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly-duties, it is not my purpoſe here to treat of them. And if any ſhall object, That this exerciſe in the Morning, requires more time than they can ſpare, being forced to ariſe to their labour aſſoon as they awake. I anſwer, Chriſtians may abound in theſe things, as their oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions will allow them. Some, I know, cannot ſpend ſo much time in them as others, but they may be the briefer; and if they ſhould have no more time to ſpare, than while they are putting on their cloaths, they may briefly run over ſome ſuch
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:121241:45"/>things in their thoughts, as I have directed them to, and make a ſupply to the want of time, by a more <hi>earn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt intention of their minds,</hi> to what they are exerciſed in.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <p>HAving in the foregoing <hi>Dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions</hi> commended the work of <hi>Self-examination</hi> to Chriſtians, as an exerciſe which may juſtly chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge a part of their ſolitary hours, and conſidering how unskilfull ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny are therein, and yet how need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full it is for getting and maintaining aſſurance, which is not only ſo ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally deſired of all Chriſtians, but of ſuch uſe to us, in the perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of <hi>Duties,</hi> bearing <hi>Afflictions,</hi> reſiſting <hi>Temptations:</hi> (three things wherein our Chriſtian buſineſs chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly lies) I have thought good to add ſomething here for the help of the weak therein: I know many have at large treated of this thing, and to
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:121241:45"/>more ſatisfaction then I can here expect to give: yet it will (I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve) be an advantage to ſome, to have theſe brief Directions at hand, and others which need them not, may let them alone, and they will be no burden to them. I ſhall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prize what I have to ſay herein un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der theſe two Directions.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Make choice of fit rules to meaſure your condition by.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Be carefull rightly to apply your ſelves to theſe Rules, that you may make a true judgement of your condition thereby.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For the firſt, The <hi>Rule</hi> that you meaſure your ſelf by, muſt be nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>too long,</hi> nor <hi>too ſhort,</hi> but <hi>ade<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quate</hi> to the ſtate of a Chriſtian; that is, it muſt not be ſo long as that all Chriſtians cannot reach it, nor ſo ſhort as that it will not reach a true Chriſtian, but ſuch as will fit every ſincere believer, and none elſe. Some judge of themſelves by
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:121241:46"/>ſuch trials or evidences, as are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petent only to thoſe that are of an high growth in Chriſtianity, and have attained to a great meaſure of grace: Theſe hearing ſome (per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps) glorying in their ſpiritual en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyments; and attainments (the teſtimony of the Spirit, the ſweet raviſhments of their ſouls in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with Jeſus Chriſt, their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of the world, (whether juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly or no, God knows.) And others in deſcribing the ſtate of a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, ſhewing rather what of <hi>right</hi> it ſhould be, then what <hi>indeed</hi> it is, what Chriſtians ought to be; rather than what they find themſelves to be. Or it may be reading in Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture the high ſtrains of others de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion, as <hi>David</hi>'s <hi>panting after God,</hi> Pſal. 42.1, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> His <hi>following hard after him,</hi> Pſal. 63.8. His <hi>dwelling with God by heavenly Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditations,</hi> Pſal. 139.17, 18. <hi>Paul</hi>'s <hi>holy zeal,</hi> Act. 20.24. His <hi>deſire of
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:121241:46"/>being with Chriſt in glory,</hi> Phil. 1.23. The ſtability and evenneſs of his ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit in <hi>every condition,</hi> Phil. 4.12. They begin to lament their own condition; alas, it is not thus with me; how unlike am I to others of the children of God? Theſe are things which I am ſo farre from ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving attained to, that I deſpair of ever reaching them. But I may (with a little alteration of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles words, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.12.) ſay of theſe, <hi>That meaſuring themſelves with others, they are not wiſe.</hi> Theſe things may ſerve for the <hi>trial</hi> of the <hi>growth</hi> of their grace, not of the <hi>truth</hi> of it: They may diſcover their imperfections, not their unſound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs: They may be matter of humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation and emulation to ſuch as have not attained thereto, but not of diſcouragement or deſpair. O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers on the other hand, bleſs them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in a fair civil deportment, in a ſpecious performance of duties,
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:121241:47"/>of juſtice and charity towards men, and piety towards God. Now, theſe things are good, and it is both honourable to our Chriſtian profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and comfortable to our ſelves, to have the teſtimony of our conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences concerning theſe things, but theſe alone do not reach the ſtate of a true believer; <hi>Paul</hi> attained thus far before his converſion, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.5, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> So that you ſee without a care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full obſervation of this firſt Rule, which I have ſet down; We ſhall be in danger, either of diſquieting our ſelves with <hi>needleſs fears,</hi> or flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering our ſelves with vain and <hi>groundleſs hopes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>You muſt carefully apply your ſelves to theſe Rules.</hi> If a man have the moſt exact meaſure or rule, if he do not rightly apply what he hath to meaſure thereunto, but either ruffle it up, or ſtretch it too much out, he will never take a right mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of it. Chriſtians are uſually
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:121241:47"/>very inquiſitive after true Marks or Evidences of a juſtified perſon, and when they come to a Miniſter to conſult about their ſpiritual condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or hear them upon an Uſe of Examination, they expect preſently to hear, whether they ſhall be ſaved or damned: as if Miniſters could as infallibly tell them their future con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, as Conjurers pretend to tell men their Fortune; when alas, after all the Directions that we are able to give, the greateſt work remains for Chriſtians to do themſelves; and if they be not faithfull to themſelves therein, it is impoſſible for us to help them.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Then labour to be well ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with your own hearts, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve diligently the carriage of them, their riſings to, or cloſing with the baits of Satan: their compliance with temptations: their reſentments after ſlips or falls, how they are affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted with them, the outgoings of
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:121241:48"/>them towards God, and towards the Creature, what are their uſual haunts. In ſhort, be as curious and critical in obſerving your ſelves, as thoſe who are the greateſt buſie bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies in other mens, matters, can be in the obſervation of others; that ſo you may not be ſtrangers at home, but may according to the ſage pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of the <hi>Heathen, Know your ſelves.</hi> This is the beſt knowledge, next to the knowledge of God in Chriſt, <hi>Multae ſcientiae hominum, ſed nulla melior eſt illa quâ cognoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cit homo ſeipſum.</hi> Bern. <hi>de inter. Do. cap.</hi> 29. <hi>princ.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Do not judge your ſelves by any particular action, or by the frame of your ſpirit at ſome ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons; for an hypocrite may ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times do that which is materially good, as a godly man may ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times do that which is evil; whereof <hi>David, Samſon, Peter,</hi> and others in Scripture, are ſad inſtances; ſo a wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:121241:48"/>man may ſometimes have his heart in a ſerious frame, under the ſmart of ſome <hi>outward affliction,</hi> (when ſenſeconvinces them of that, which at other times they are back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward to believe) as <hi>Pſal.</hi> 78.34. or under powerfull convictions of the Word, as thoſe compared with the <hi>ſtony ground,</hi> Luk. 8.13. So a godly man may ſometimes be in a wofull frame, as <hi>David,</hi> 2 Sa. 11. one would have thought that had never known him before, that he had been a man of a ſeared conſcience, that had ſung away care, and baniſhed the fear of God from before his eyes, and <hi>Jonah</hi> was little better, <hi>Jon.</hi> 4.9. but we muſt obſerve, what is the conſtant habitual frame of our hearts, and the ordinary carriage of our lives. A godly man in Scripture is deſcribed, not by his particular actions, but by his walking, which imports his ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary courſe, and the general tenour of his converſation, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 1.1. &amp; 119.1.
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:121241:49"/>
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.1. Indeed to be frequently overtaken with ſin, is an ill ſign, yet to determine, how oft a godly man may be overtaken by temptation, or how many ſinfull actions are incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent with ſincerity, is as impoſſible in <hi>Divinity,</hi> as to determine in <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality,</hi> how many <hi>actions</hi> go to the acquiring of an <hi>habit.</hi> In ſuch a caſe there is much need of a ſpiritual diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning, and a prudent weighing of particular circumſtances, ſorthe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of a right and ſafe judgment.</p>
               <p n="3">3. In judging our ſelves, we muſt have ſome reſpect to natural temper and inclinations, and to the tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions which our condition layes us moſt open to. A little ſugar ſerves for ſweet wines, but there is more required to ſweeten that which is more ſharp; ſo, a little grace makes a great ſhew in ſome tempers, and a great deal ſcarce appears in others; as an eminent man ſaid, of one now in Heaven, That he had grace
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:121241:49"/>enough for ten other men, but ſcarce enough for himſelf, which he would himſelf bewail, ſaying, he had ſuch a crooked nature, that if God had not given him grace, none would have been able to live a day with him. So likewiſe the more in of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſive lives of ſome men may be imputed rather to the want of tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptations, then to a greater meaſure of grace. The truth is, a mans ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity is much diſcovered, in keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him <hi>from his own iniquity,</hi> Pſal. 18.23. (<hi>Eſt virtus placitis abſtinu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſſe bonis.</hi> Ovid.) and overcoming temptations, when he is <hi>aſſaulted therewith,</hi> Prov. 24.10. Yet let a man have an equal tincture of ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pernatural grace in all the affections of his ſoul; Let the Spirit of God diffuſe it ſelf like leaven, indifferent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly through the whole lump; yea, let a man beſtow alſo the moſt care in watching his own heart, in ſome
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:121241:50"/>particular outgoings of it, he ſhall notwithſtanding find himſelf moſt defective in that very thing; and (as D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Preſton</hi> rightly obſerves) thoſe ſins are with the moſt difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty mortified, which our natural temper doth moſt diſpoſe us to. Some affections are more predomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant in one age, ſome in another: There are <hi>youthfull luſts,</hi> 2 Tim. 2.22. and infirmities more proper to old age, as covetouſneſs, peeviſhnes, fear, ſuſpicion, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> So God likewiſe ſuits mens tempers many times, to the imploiments which he reſerves them for. <hi>Moſes</hi> was the <hi>weekeſt man on earth,</hi> Num. 12.3. and ſo he had need to be, who had ſuch a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe provoking generation of men to deal with. <hi>Luther</hi> was a fierce hot ſpirited man, and he was there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by fitted for the work which he had to do, which was to ſtand as a bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen wall againſt the whole world;
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:121241:50"/>and choler is not only <hi>Cos ingenii,</hi> to whet the wit (as the Philoſophers ſay) but it adds vigour and activity to mens ſpirits, fitting them for acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as the ſting in the Bee, without which ſhe is but a drone. And I am inclinable to think, that <hi>Luther</hi> had as much of the <hi>grace</hi> of <hi>meekneſs,</hi> as of <hi>charity</hi> or <hi>bounty;</hi> but being of a <hi>generous ſpirit</hi> naturally, he would ſay, he never found the leaſt inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to covetouſneſs, whereas his paſſionate fierceneſs made his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation very unpleaſing, and put poor <hi>Melancthon</hi> to cry out,
<q>Vince animos, iramque tuam, qui caetera vincis.</q> So for temptations, they may make thoſe graces yield, wherein Chriſtians (if in any) do moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell, as we ſee in the caſe of <hi>Job.</hi> who was an <hi>eminent example of pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience,</hi> Jam. 5.11. yet we do not
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:121241:51"/>obſerve in his ſtory that any grace which he had gave out ſo much as his patience, becauſe that bare the burden and heat of the day; his condition did moſt exerciſe that. And this muſt be obſerved both in judging our ſelves, and others; thou perhaps ſeeſt more failings in another than in thy ſelf; be it ſo, and that thou art not partial to thy ſelf, yet this may be, not becauſe thou haſt more <hi>grace,</hi> but becauſe he hath more <hi>temptations.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. Take heed that thy grace do not make thee to think thy ſelf graceleſs, or at leaſt leſs gracious then thou art. There are ſome things which make Chriſtians ſeem leſſe in their own eyes, then they are: and that is the reaſon why we ordinarily hear thoſe, who may be thought to have the beſt hearts, making the ſaddeſt complaints againſt themſelves. There are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:121241:51"/>graces, the more a Chriſtian hath of them, the worſe he thinks of himſelf: 1. The more <hi>knowledge</hi> a Chriſtian hath, the more he ſees of the extent of the Law of God, and the more clear apprehenſion he hath of his duty; and ſo he ſees more of his own defects. We ſhall ſee that this made <hi>Paul</hi> think worſe of himſelf after his converſion, then he did before; if we compare <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.5, 6. with <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.9. 2. The more <hi>livelineſs</hi> and <hi>tenderneſs of ſpirit</hi> a Chriſtian hath, the more ſenſible he is of his corruption; as thoſe who are more tender and delicate, are more troubled at ſuch things as are offenſive to them, then thoſe who are of a more dull heavy temper. 3. The more <hi>humility</hi> a man hath, the meaner thoughts he hath of himſelf, and of his ſervices. 4. The more <hi>love</hi> a man hath to Jeſus Chriſt, the more free he is of his ſervice to
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:121241:52"/>him; and, ſo more affected with his own infirmities, when he falls ſhort of what he hath an heart to do for him. 5. The more the ſoul <hi>bungers and thirſts after righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> the leſs doth any meaſure of grace ſeem, which it hath already received: as a covetous man, who thirſts after more wealth, is always complaining of his poverty, and thinks that to be nothing which he hath already. And as the beſt Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians do oft thus wrong themſelves; ſo others that have leſs of theſe gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, are prone to think too highly of themſelves.</p>
               <p>Now before I conclude, I muſt ſay ſomething in anſwer to a Queſtion, which will be eaſily occaſioned, by what hath been already ſpoken. Since we are to try our ſelves by an adaequate Rule, and by ſuch Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences as are competent to all juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied perſons, and to them only, <hi>What
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:121241:52"/>are thoſe proper Characters of a true Chriſtian?</hi> I cannot here diſcourſe at large of the ſeveral graces of the Spirit, and ſhew how they may be diſtinguiſhed from their counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeits: yet that I may do ſomething towards the ſatisfaction of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans in this particular, I ſhall firſt endeavour to explain the true Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of ſaving Faith, and then to diſcover ſo far as I am able, what is the genuine temper and diſpoſition of a child of God.</p>
               <p>For the firſt, It is that which our ſalvation depends upon, and I chuſe alwayes to deſcribe it, in the words of our common <hi>Catéchiſm,</hi> which I would never willingly ſwerve from, but keep cloſe to, that ſo Chriſtians may be more ſecure in entertaining the truth, and free from ſuſpicion of being miſguided by the ſingular notions of a private ſpirit. Now there it is deſcribed, <hi>A ſaving grace,
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:121241:53"/>whereby we receive Jeſus-Chriſt, and reſt upon him for ſalvation, as he is offered to us in the Gospel.</hi> I confeſs, I do not look upon this as an acu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate definition of Faith, properly ſo called; yet, as conſonant to the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures manner of teaching. Divinity being a practical Diſcipline, the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt in Scripture doth not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſine things, as a Philoſopher, by their <hi>genus &amp; differentia,</hi> but by their <hi>ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects.</hi> See the Scriptures definition of <hi>wiſdom,</hi> Job 28.28. of <hi>knowledg,</hi> Jer. 16.22. of <hi>faith,</hi> Heb. 11.1. of the <hi>fear of God,</hi> Pro. 8.13. of the <hi>love of God,</hi> 1 Jo. 5.3. of <hi>Religion,</hi> Jam. 1.27. Faith is properly an aſſent to any thing upon the authority of him that affirms it, and ſo more particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly, divine Faith is an aſſent to any truth upon Gods authority: but becauſe it is not ſo eaſie to make a right judgment of the acts of the underſtanding, as they have an exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtence
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:121241:53"/>in their Subject, however we may ſpeak ſomething of the differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of them, as they are in their <hi>Idea.</hi> The Scripture takes notice of them when they come lower into the Will, and obſerves what work they make, or what effect they have there, and thereby judges, whether they be right or no. But let me a little explain this deſcription of Faith, that ſo we may the better underſtand the nature of it. It is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led a <hi>Grace,</hi> becauſe it is a <hi>gift free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly given,</hi> Eph. 2.8. <hi>a ſaving grace,</hi> becauſe it is one of thoſe things which accompany ſalvation, <hi>Mark</hi> 16.16. It is ſaid to be a <hi>grace where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we receive Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> Now I confeſs I do not ſee that the place uſually alledged for the proof here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.12. doth convincingly prove it, ſince it may be otherwiſe expounded: what inconvenience would follow, if we ſhould take the
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:121241:54"/>word <hi>receive</hi> in a larger ſenſe, as it is uſed <hi>Matth.</hi> 10.14. and the words following not <hi>exegeticè,</hi> as an expoſition of what went before, but <hi>reſtrictivè,</hi> as a limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation thereof. The like reſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction we have, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 145.18. yet Faith may properly be called <hi>a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving of Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> it being the firſtact of the Will about the <hi>means</hi> leading to our end; which act the <hi>Schoolmen</hi> call <hi>Election</hi> (hence I ſuppoſe Doctor <hi>Ames, Rolloc,</hi> and others borrow this term, which they make uſe of in explaining the Nature of Faith,) which they make to be, an <hi>acce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pting</hi> of this or that means, or chooſing it before others, (by the approbation of the judgment) as beſt conducing to the attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of our end. Or to ſpeak more plainly, and properly (which is beſt,) if we conſider Jeſus
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:121241:54"/>Chriſt as the <hi>gift of God, offered to us in the Gospel,</hi> (as is expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in the fore-going deſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,) Faith is our receiving of him, accepting of Gods offer, <hi>Taking hold on Gods Covenant,</hi> ſtriking hands with him, conſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing freely that Chriſt ſhall be ours. I cannot ſtand here to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine how neceſſary our acce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptation is, to the making a thing our own, or a gift properly to us: Or, whether a man may in any caſe have, not only <hi>Jus<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ad rem,</hi> or <hi>title,</hi> but <hi>Jus in re,</hi> or <hi>poſſeſſion,</hi> without his conſent or acceptance: remembring the end of my diſcourſe, which ſuch diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſitions would have little ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency to. <hi>Vid.</hi> Meſtrezat. <hi>de la Vertu de la Foy.</hi> pag. 97. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to proceed; It is added in this Deſcription of Faith, <hi>That it is a resting upon Jeſus Chriſt
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:121241:55"/>for Salvation.</hi> The former words do aptly expreſs the firſt <hi>Act</hi> of <hi>Faith,</hi> which is the ſouls fixing, or pitching upon Chriſt in its choice, as the only ſufficient means of Salvation. Theſe words hold forth the <hi>porro eſſe,</hi> (as I may ſpeak) of <hi>Faith,</hi> or the <hi>conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued Act of it,</hi> upon the ſouls <hi>former choice.</hi> So that as a lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned man, (Doctor <hi>Wallis</hi> in his moſt ingenuous anſwer to the Lord <hi>Brook</hi>) doth well obſerve, It is all one whether we make Faith to be a <hi>receiving</hi> of Chriſt for our Saviour, or a <hi>reſting</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him for Salvation. Some chooſe to expreſs it by the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Act, ſome by the latter: for the latter doth neceſſarily <hi>ſuppoſe</hi> the former, and the former im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately <hi>inferre</hi> the latter, if we conſider how Chriſt is offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the Goſpel, that is as the
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:121241:55"/>
                  <hi>only Saviour,</hi> Act. 4.12. and as a <hi>ſufficient Saviour,</hi> Heb. 7.25. But here obſerve, That by a <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting on Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> we do not mean a <hi>confirmed hope,</hi> or a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain expectation of Salvation by Jeſus Chriſt: This is an <hi>effect</hi> of aſſurance, but the <hi>leaning, rol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, ſtaying</hi> of the ſoul upon Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, which we may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive of, by the notion which the Scripture oft holds it forth under, a <hi>looking to him,</hi> or <hi>ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving our eyes towards him.</hi> Read 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 20.12. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 121.1. &amp; 123.1, 2. <hi>Iſai.</hi> 45.22. <hi>Jonah</hi> 2.4. <hi>Micha</hi> 7.7. This <hi>Act</hi> the ſoul may put forth without <hi>Aſſurance.</hi> Of the Difference between theſe two <hi>Acts,</hi> ſee Doctor <hi>Ward, De Fide Justificante,</hi> cap. 8. &amp; 23. And (in Engliſh) Doctor <hi>Bolton, Of the Nature of Faith,</hi> pag. 60, 61. This latter <hi>Act</hi> is aptly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:121241:56"/>by Maſter <hi>Cotton,</hi> (a man of much Chriſtian experience) on 1 <hi>John</hi> 5.10. whoſe words I ſhall ſet down, becauſe they are ſuited to the capacity and experience of weak Chriſtians. [<hi>There is</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>a believing on Chriſt, when the heart doth not yet reſt on him, but roll it ſelf on him; and that may be done while the heart is yet in motion; reſting is a ſetled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of condition, but rolling is an unſetled tumbling about, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times one way, and ſometimes another: yet ſuch a Chriſtian be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieves on Chriſt, becauſe he is rolling towards him, that ſo he may lie on him,</hi> Pſal. 37.5. Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit thy way to the Lord; <hi>ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Original it is,</hi> Roll thy way upon the Lord, <hi>lean thy ſoul that way, which is done by rolling thy ſelf towards him, that thou mayeſt reſt upon him,</hi> Pro. 16.3.
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:121241:56"/>
                  <hi>a man may be ſaid to leane on that whereon be is not ſetled.</hi>] And indeed the Hebrews expreſs the Act of Affiance by the word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> which ſignifies to <hi>roll,</hi> Pſal. 22.8. Let the Reader only ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, that M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Cotton</hi> takes <hi>rest<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> in a ſtricter ſenſe, than we do in the former deſcription, when he oppoſeth it to <hi>rolling,</hi> he underſtands thereby the <hi>Affi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of Hope,</hi> which <hi>follows Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance.</hi> To come then to the Queſtion, Doſt thou freely accept of Jeſus Chriſt for thy Saviour? Art thou heartily willing to ſtrike hands with God in the Covenant of Grace? And though thou haſt not a particular Aſſurance that Chriſt will ſave thee, Doſt thou look towards him? Doſt thou roll thy ſelf upon him, though unbelieving thoughts re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn oft, and preſſe hard upon
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:121241:57"/>thee? (As a man may roll a burden upon ſomething, and it may return oft upon him again, before he can make it lie.) Thy condition is very hopefull. But here it will be objected, That there are ſome that for a time believe, and yet fall <hi>away,</hi> Luk. 8.13. I confeſſe this caſe is very difficult, yet I ſhall give the Objection a fair hearing before I anſwer it. Indeed I do believe that there is a real intrinſick difference between the firſt Act of <hi>Justifying Faith,</hi> and the <hi>Faith</hi> of a <hi>Temporary:</hi> Yet ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny times this difference is not diſcernable by the perſons them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves which ſo believe; That you may underſtand what I mean: Suppoſe two men under the ſame affliction, as the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> Pſal. 78.31. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> or both hearing the Word together, as <hi>Luke</hi> 8.13.
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:121241:57"/>Theſe men may be ſo wrought upon, as that they may both make the ſame reſolution (as ſeems to themſelves,) with alike ſeriouſneſs, and without diſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulation, freely taking Chriſt for their Saviour, or caſting themſelves upon him for Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, they may have the ſame apprehenſions concerning their own Acts themſelves, one of theſe may <hi>fall,</hi> the other <hi>perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere.</hi> This is that which hath been long ſince taught: ſee <hi>Dyke</hi> on the <hi>Deceitfullneſſe of the Heart,</hi> Chap. 20. where ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> Pſalm. 78.34. he ſayes, <hi>They ſpake as they thought, and meant to doe.</hi> See likewiſe more ſully on this, Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor <hi>Jackson,</hi> of <hi>Faith,</hi> Chap. 7. Paragr. 14. And it is general<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly acknowledged, That there are not only <hi>groſſe</hi> Hypocrites, that
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:121241:58"/>deceive others, but <hi>cloſe</hi> Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites that deceive themſelves. But how comes it to paſſe, that one <hi>ſtands,</hi> and another <hi>falls?</hi> I anſwer, As it is in colours, two things may appear at firſt of the <hi>ſame</hi> colour, one <hi>abides,</hi> the other <hi>fades.</hi> Now the <hi>Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> of this is, there is an <hi>addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of ſome <hi>ingredient,</hi> which gives the one a more laſting tin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture than the other; one is di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in <hi>grain,</hi> the other hath but an <hi>ordinary</hi> die. So to thoſe <hi>ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional Motives</hi> which are the <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducements</hi> both to the one, and to the other to believe; there is in one, the <hi>addition</hi> of a <hi>spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual infuſion,</hi> which gives to one mans Faith a true and abiding <hi>tincture;</hi> There is <hi>a ſeed of God abiding in him,</hi> 1 John 3.9. You will ſay, If it be <hi>thus,</hi> How ſhall we ever come to any <hi>Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty</hi>
                  <pb n="103" facs="tcp:121241:58"/>concerning our <hi>own</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, if we may be deceived in the <hi>Acts</hi> of our <hi>own</hi> ſouls? If it be ſaid, That we muſt know the truth of our Faith by the trial of it in ſtanding out againſt temptations: This is ſomething indeed. But what time muſt we take for the tryall of our Faith? When may we confirm the truth of it with a <hi>probatum eſt?</hi> When ſhall I know that the worſt try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all is over? Some ſtood out in the time of Queen <hi>Maries</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution, which afterwards fell away in time of liberty and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity: <hi>Joab</hi> turned not after <hi>Abſalom,</hi> but he turned after <hi>Adonijah.</hi> Though I turn not after one temptation, I may after another. Yea a leſſe temptation may overcome me after I have ſtood out againſt greater, <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſus majora vigilantibus quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:121241:59"/>incautis minuta ſubrepunt. Aug.</hi> As <hi>Lot</hi> retained his inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grity in <hi>Sodome,</hi> but miſcarried when he was only with his own family, <hi>Gen.</hi> 19.33. And ſo we muſt conclude, There is no aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance to be had (without ſpecial revelation,) by this means while we are in this life, <hi>Dicique bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus, ante obitum nemo,</hi> &amp;c. Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving thus urged the Objection with all its ſtrength. I anſwer, There is yet another way for the tryall of our Faith, although ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny times in the firſt Act of Faith, (as <hi>Streſo</hi> obſerves) the ſoul is not ſo deliberate, it doth not ſtand to debate the matter long, or to form <hi>Syllogiſmes,</hi> but preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with the apprehenſion of its danger, layes hold on what is next to ſave it, and flees for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuge to the <hi>hope that is ſet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it:</hi> yet afterwards, when it
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:121241:59"/>comes more deliberately to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cognize its former Act, (which he is ſuppoſed to have opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity for, who is enquiring after the ſincerity of his Faith,) in this recognition or renewing the Act of Faith, there is that which doth clearly difference it from a temporaries Faith. Therefore there are <hi>three</hi> things which I ſhall lay down, which may ſerve both to direct Chriſtians in the exerciſe of their Faith, and the ſre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent renewing of their <hi>hold</hi> on Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, and to try the ſinceri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Faith, in the renewed Acts of it.</p>
               <p>Firſt, <hi>Sit downe, and count the coſt of being the Diſciples of Christ,</hi> Luk. 14.26. And ſee in the two fore-going verſes the occaſion of theſe words. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, That Chriſt will <hi>rule</hi> you if he <hi>ſave</hi> you; and that his
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:121241:60"/>Laws are not ſuited to your car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall intereſts, or corrupt luſts: We muſt take Chriſt, as he is <hi>of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered in the Gospel,</hi> God hath condeſcended there, as farre as he will; he cannot be brought to lower termes. Indeed in the firſt Act of Faith, uſually the ſoul hath chief reſpect to <hi>pardon,</hi> as that which it is then moſt ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible of the want of: the ſoul therein <hi>flees for refuge to Chriſt, Heb.</hi> 6.18. <hi>Flees from the wrath to come,</hi> Matth. 3.7. But though pardoning grace be <hi>Ratio motiva,</hi> or the firſt inducement to bring us to Jeſus Chriſt, yet it muſt not be <hi>ratio terminativa,</hi> or that which muſt bound our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires after him. Here now the Hypocrite fails, when he comes to ſee what it is to be a <hi>Diſciple of Chriſt,</hi> he repents of his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, and comes off with a
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:121241:60"/>
                  <hi>non putâram:</hi> Chriſt had many followers, while they ſaw his mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles, and he was likely to be made an earthly King, but <hi>they turned their backs on him,</hi> when they underſtood the <hi>Nature</hi> of his <hi>ſervice,</hi> John 6.16, 60, 66. Many under the laſh of afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, or the convictions of the Word, betake themſelves to Chriſt for <hi>ſhelter,</hi> but afterwards deſpiſe the <hi>ſimplicity of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spel,</hi> and the <hi>ſtrictneſſe of holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſſe;</hi> as one that in a ſtorme takes ſhelter in a Cottage, where he would not be afterwards per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded to dwell; or borrows a Coat, which after the ſhowr is over he would ſcorn to wear. But <hi>Paul,</hi> when he came to make a recognition of his former act, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.7, 8. He <hi>ſtands to his former choice</hi> and <hi>judgement, Thoſe things</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:121241:61"/>were gain to me, I counted loſſe for Chriſt: Yea, doubtleſſe, and I doe count all things loſſe, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, <hi>Bring your wills to a firm determinate reſolution,</hi> Pſ. 119.106. Acts 11.23. When men have not brought their wills to this conſiſtency, they are like fluid bodies, which, as we ſay, <hi>Facilè continentur alienis termi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis,</hi> do yield to the form or fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure of every veſſel which they are put into. So theſe <hi>double<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minded men are unſtable as wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> like <hi>Reuben,</hi> Gen. 49.4. fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhioning themſelves to every oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currence, which they meet with, receiving the impreſſion of eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thing that is applied to them; when the Word comes with <hi>pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er</hi> upon their ſouls, they are quite born down with it, and are <hi>all for Chriſt;</hi> and when the <hi>world</hi>
                  <pb n="109" facs="tcp:121241:61"/>and <hi>ſinne</hi> have an opportunity to ſet upon them, they <hi>yeeld thereto.</hi> This was (as <hi>Maldo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate</hi> ſaith) the fault of the ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ground, they had not <hi>Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam &amp; profundam voluntatem:</hi> ſuch unſtable men invite tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptations, whereas a firm reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion <hi>prevents them;</hi> it <hi>diſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rages the importunity of men, Acts</hi> 21.14. Yea, <hi>It puts Satan to flight,</hi> James 4.7. <hi>Vid.</hi> Guil. Pariſienſ. <hi>de Tentat. &amp; Reſest. prine.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly, <hi>Commit the keeping of your ſouls to God in well-do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> 1 Pet. 4.18. None fitter than <hi>Peter</hi> to give this counſell, who had found by experience, how vain it is to make reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in our <hi>own ſtrength,</hi> Matth. 26.33, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> We muſt not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>believe on Chriſt for Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> but to be <hi>k<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> by his power
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:121241:62"/>to Salvation,</hi> 1 Pet. 1.5. and God will not fail ſuch as do thus <hi>wait on him,</hi> Iſai. 40.28. though others (that like young men are moſt confident of their own ſtrength) may fall. Now then, Canſt thou in ſincerity goe to God, and ſay? Lord, I know, that it is no eaſie matter to <hi>deny my ſelf,</hi> to <hi>cut off my right hand,</hi> to <hi>pluck out my right eye,</hi> to <hi>part with thoſe ſinnes which are moſt uſefull, moſt dear to me;</hi> yet this <hi>I muſt do,</hi> if I will be the <hi>Diſciple of Chriſt;</hi> yet having counted both the loſſe and the gain, which I ſhall thereby have, I <hi>freely chooſe Chriſt for my por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> let him do what he will with me, and bring me to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven which way ſeems good to him; I am reſolved to <hi>cleave to him,</hi> through the aſſiſtance of thy grace, <hi>Who</hi> (though I am not
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:121241:62"/>able to think any thing of my ſelf, yet) <hi>art able to keep that good thing which I commit to thee,</hi> 2 Tim. 1.12. I know not what a ſoul ſhould do more in the act of Faith, if ten Heavens de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pended upon it.</p>
               <p>I will very briefly adde ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of the <hi>temper</hi> of a gracious ſoul, 1. It hath a <hi>true love to Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> 1 Cor. 16.22. Joh. 14.21. and this is ſooner diſcer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by the <hi>inward inclination</hi> and <hi>affections of the heart,</hi> than the <hi>outward actions</hi> of the life: Doſt thou breathe after more inward communion with him? Doſt thou lament inwardly after him? Though it may be thou haſt not ſuch a melting ſpirit as M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Brad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford,</hi> who could ſit and weep at Dinner, till the tears fell on his trencher, becauſe he could love God no more, yet is it a reall
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:121241:63"/>trouble to thee, that thou canſt love him no more, nor do him better ſervice? Such a diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion I am ſure cannot be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out active endeavours: but theſe are <hi>diſcoveries</hi> of a <hi>Divine Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</hi> 2. A gracious ſoul is <hi>care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to pleaſe God,</hi> though it doth not know whether God love it, or no; This is a true filial diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, when a Child is willing to pleaſe its Father, and is ready to do any thing wherein it may be ſerviceable to him, though its Father: will not (it may be) give it a good look, nor take any no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of it: if a ſoul find this di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpoſition in it ſelf, let it <hi>ſtay it ſelf upon its God,</hi> hold <hi>thy ſelf by him,</hi> he <hi>bids thee, he will not caſt thee off.</hi> Read <hi>Iſai.</hi> 50.10. 3. A Child of God <hi>hates ſinne,</hi> God <hi>hates it,</hi> Jer. 44.4. and he that is <hi>joyned</hi> to the Lord is <hi>one
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:121241:63"/>Spirit,</hi> 1 Cor. 6.16. And this is diſcovered in a general averſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>from all ſinne,</hi> hatred is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the whole <hi>kind:</hi> Some men <hi>fear</hi> ſinne, but they do not <hi>hate</hi> it, many are afraid to be where ſome Creatures are, leſt they ſhould do them hurt; but if they are ſure that they are faſt chained, they are well enough; but where there is an <hi>Antipathy,</hi> ſuch cannot endure to be near thoſe Creatures, though they are ſure they cannot hurt them: So many are afraid of ſuch ſinnes as may <hi>damn</hi> them, or bring them to <hi>ſhame,</hi> or ſome other incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venience in this <hi>world;</hi> but a godly man abhorres his <hi>ſecret cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions,</hi> which he knows the beſt that go to Heaven are trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled with, whilſt they are here, and which he knows will not hinder his worldly intereſt; or
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:121241:64"/>as others aptly illuſtrate it, many are afraid to touch a <hi>cole</hi> when it is <hi>hot,</hi> for fear of <hi>burning</hi> them: but thoſe who are more curious cannot endure to touch it when it is <hi>cold,</hi> leaſt it ſhould <hi>black</hi> them: A wicked man is afraid to meddle with ſuch ſins as may <hi>damn</hi> him; a godly man is offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with ſuch ſins as may <hi>defile</hi> him. Thus, <hi>Reader,</hi> I have en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured to help thee in this great work; but if thou doſt not ſet thy ſelf with all diligence here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, my labour is in vain: Yea, ſo it will be, unleſs the Lord ſet in by his <hi>own Spirit,</hi> to put for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the ſame. Though the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet had told <hi>David</hi> plainly, That the <hi>Lord had put away his ſinne,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 12.13. that would not ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence the clamours of a guilty con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, nor quiet and calm his troubled ſpirit, but he muſt ſue
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:121241:64"/>to God, to <hi>reſtore to him the joy of his ſalvation,</hi> Pſal. 51.12.</p>
               <p>Some thoughts have offer'd themſelves to me of inſerting in this Edition ſome practical caſes, which might be occaſioned by what is ſuppoſed in the fore-going Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe, and is now more generally re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived amongſt Proteſtants then formerly, <hi>viz.</hi> That Aſſurance doth not always follow upon Faith, much leſs conſtitute it? Hereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it might be juſtly queſtioned, How Chriſtians that want Aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance can pray in Faith, come boldly to the throne of grace, approach with comfort to the Lords Table, rejoyce alwayes in the Lord? <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which ſeem to be duties incumbent on every Chriſtian: But I have put off ſuch thoughts at preſent, intending to reſerve theſe, with many other things, for another Treatiſe, which
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:121241:65"/>I ſhall <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> impart to the world, as I ſhall ſee occaſion, and have opportunity, and end this matter with the deſire of <hi>Bernard, Med. cap.</hi> 5. <hi>Cum coram Deo in lachry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis te maceraveris precor te, ut memor ſis mei,</hi> when thou affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cteſt thy ſelf in tears before the Lord, I pray thee remember me, leaſt when I have written and preached to others, I my ſelf ſhould be a caſtaway.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:121241:65"/>
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>EPiſt. Ded. p. 5. l. 12. for 9. r. 19. p. 7. l. 8. r. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 73.26. p. 8. l. 1. r. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. there is ſomewhere in the Epiſtle <hi>examples</hi> for <hi>example.</hi> p. 11. l. 19. for <hi>ſi.</hi> r. <hi>ſic.</hi> p. 28. l. 14. r. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 25.15. p. 30. l. 4. r. <hi>may.</hi> p. 31. l. 14. r. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.20. p. 39. l. 21. r. <hi>capiunt.</hi> p. 53. l. 10. r. <hi>ſoyl.</hi> p. 55. l. 1. dele <hi>ſome.</hi> p. 55. ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is miſplaced: after <hi>Mal</hi> 3.16. adde <hi>Ita fabulantur,</hi> &amp;c. to the ſecond head.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
